LIFE OF CATO.
<persName id="#i.
cato's_family">I.
Cato's family</persName> derived the origin of its splendour and reputation from <persName id="#his_great-grandfather_cato">his great-grandfather Cato</persName>, <persName id="#a_man">a man</persName> who had reputation and <persName id="#power_chief">power chief</persName> among the <personGrp id="#romans">Romans</personGrp> by reason of his merit, as it has been written in his Life.
Cato was left an orphan with <persName id="#his_brother">his brother</persName> <persName id="#caepio">Caepio</persName> and <persName id="#a_sister">a sister</persName> <personGrp id="#porcia">Porcia</personGrp>.
Servilia also was <persName id="#a_sister">a sister</persName> of <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> by <persName id="#the_same_mother">the same mother</persName>.
All of them were brought up and lived with <persName id="#livius_drusus">Livius Drusus</persName>, <persName id="#their_mother's_uncle">their mother's uncle</persName>, who was then <persName id="#the_chief_political_leader">the chief political leader</persName>; for he was <persName id="#a_most_powerful_speaker">a most powerful speaker</persName>, and <persName id="#also_a_man">also a man</persName> of the best regulated habits, and in lofty bearing inferior to no <persName id="#roman">Roman</persName>.
It is said that <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> from his childhood both in his voice and the expression of his countenance and even in his amusements gave indication of a character immovable and impassive and firm in everything.
His purposes displayed a strength in accomplishing his ends which was above his age: and while he was rough and stubborn towards those who attempted to flatter him, still more did he show his mastery over all who would try to terrify him by threats.
He was also difficult to move to laughter, and his countenance was seldom relaxed even into a smile; he was not quick nor prone to anger, but when he had been moved to anger, he was hard to pacify.
Accordingly when he began to learn, he was dull and slow to conceive, but when he had conceived, he held fast and remembered well.
And it is generally the case that those who have a good natural capacity are more ready at recollection, but those have a strong memory who learn with labour and trouble; for all learning is in a manner a branding on the mind.
It appears too that Cato's difficulty of persuasion made learning a matter of more labour to him; for learning is in truth a kind of passive condition, and to be easily persuaded is incident to those who have less power of resistance.
It is for this reason that <persName id="#young_men">young men</persName> are more easily persuaded than <persName id="#old_men">old men</persName>, and sick persons than those who are whole; and generally, with those in whom the doubting faculty is weakest, that which is proposed meets the readiest acceptance.
However, they say that <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> was obedient to his paedagogus and did everything that he was bid, but he would ask for the reason of everything, and inquire the Why.
His paedagogus also was <persName id="#a_good-tempered_man">a good-tempered man</persName>, and was readier at a reason than a blow: his name was <persName id="#sarpedon">Sarpedon</persName>.
II.
While <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> was still <persName id="#a_boy">a boy</persName>, the Allies of the <personGrp id="#romans">Romans</personGrp> were agitating to obtain the <personGrp id="#roman">Roman</personGrp> franchise; and a certain <persName id="#pompaedius_sillo">Pompaedius Sillo</persName>, <persName id="#a_man">a man</persName> of military talent and of the highest repute, and <persName id="#a_friend">a friend</persName> of <persName id="#drusus">Drusus</persName>, lodged with him several days, during which he became familiar with <persName id="#the_youths">the youths</persName>, and he said, "Come now, pray <persName id="#your_uncle">your uncle</persName> on our behalf to exert himself to get the franchise for us."
Now, <persName id="#caepio">Caepio</persName> with a smile nodded assent, but as <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> made no answer and looked on <persName id="#the_strangers">the strangers</persName> steadily and sternly, <persName id="#pompaedius">Pompaedius</persName> said, "But you, <persName id="#young_man">young man</persName>, what reply have you for us? Can you not help <persName id="#the_strangers">the strangers</persName> with <persName id="#your_uncle">your uncle</persName>, like <persName id="#your_brother">your brother</persName>?" As <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> still would not speak, but by his silence and his expression showed that he rejected their entreaty, <persName id="#pompaedius">Pompaedius</persName> took him up and holding him through the window as if he intended to drop him down, told him either to assent or he would let him fall, and at the same time he assumed an angry tone and several times he swung <persName id="#the_boy">the boy</persName> backwards and forwards as he held him in his hands.
Now, when <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> had borne this for some time, unmoved and fearless, <persName id="#pompaedius">Pompaedius</persName> gently putting him down said to <persName id="#his_friends">his friends</persName>, "What a blessing to <personGrp id="#italy">Italy</personGrp> that he is <persName id="#a_child">a child</persName>; for if he were <persName id="#a_man">a man</persName>, I do not think we should have a single vote among <persName id="#the_people">the people</persName>."
On another occasion when <persName id="#a_kinsman">a kinsman</persName> on his birthday invited to <persName id="#supper_other_boys">supper other boys</persName> and <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> with them, in order to pass the time they played in a part of the house by themselves, younger and older mixed together; and the game consisted of trials, and accusations, and carrying off those who were convicted.
Now, one of <persName id="#the_boys">the boys</persName> convicted, who was of a handsome presence, being dragged off by <persName id="#an_older_boy">an older boy</persName> to a chamber and shut up, called on <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> for aid.
Cato soon perceiving what was going on came to the door, and pushing through those who were standing before it and endeavouring to stop him, took <persName id="#the_boy">the boy</persName> out; and in a passion he went off home with him and <persName id="#other_boys">other boys</persName> accompanied him.
III.
<persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> was so much talked of that when <persName id="#sulla">Sulla</persName> was preparing for exhibition the sacred horse race called <personGrp id="#troja">Troja</personGrp>, in which <persName id="#youths">youths</persName> are <persName id="#the_actors">the actors</persName>, and had got together <persName id="#the_boys">the boys</persName> of noble birth and appointed <persName id="#two_captains">two captains</persName>, <persName id="#the_boys">the boys</persName> submitted to the one for <persName id="#his_mother's_sake">his mother's sake</persName>, for he was <persName id="#a_son">a son</persName> of <persName id="#metella">Metella</persName>, <persName id="#sulla's_wife">Sulla's wife</persName>; but the other, who was <persName id="#a_nephew">a nephew</persName> of <persName id="#pompeius">Pompeius</persName> and named Sextus, they would not have, nor would they go through their exercise nor follow him; and on <persName id="#sulla">Sulla</persName> asking whom they would have, they all called out "<persName id="#cato">Cato</persName>," and Sextus himself gave way and yielded the honour to <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> as his better.
It happened that <persName id="#sulla">Sulla</persName> was <persName id="#an_old_friend">an old friend</persName> of <persName id="#cato's_family">Cato's family</persName>, and sometimes he had <persName id="#the_children">the children</persName> brought to him and talked with them, a kind of friendship which he showed to few, by reason of the weight and state of the office and power that he held.
<personGrp id="#sarpedon">Sarpedon</personGrp> considering this a great matter both as regarded the honour and security of <persName id="#the_youth">the youth</persName>, constantly took <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> to pay his respects to <persName id="#sulla">Sulla</persName> at his house, which at that time to all outward appearance differed not from a place of torture for <persName id="#criminals">criminals</persName>, so great was the number of those who were dragged there and put to the rack.
Cato was at this time in his fourteenth year, and seeing the heads of persons who were said to be <persName id="#men">men</persName> of distinction brought out, and those who were present lamenting inwardly, he asked his paedagogus why <persName id="#nobody">nobody</persName> killed <persName id="#this_man">this man</persName>.
<personGrp id="#sarpedon">Sarpedon</personGrp> replied, "Because they fear him, child, more than they hate him."
"Why, then," said <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName>, "do you not give me a sword that I might kill him, and so free my country from slavery?" Hearing these words and at the same time observing his eyes and countenance to be filled with passion and resolve, <persName id="#sarpedon">Sarpedon</persName> was so afraid that henceforward he kept a close look and watch upon him, that he should not venture on any desperate measure.
Now when he was still <persName id="#a_little_boy">a little boy</persName>, and some persons asked him whom he loved most, he replied <persName id="#his_brother">his brother</persName>; when he was asked whom he loved next, he gave the same answer, <persName id="#his_brother">his brother</persName>; and so on to the third question, until the questioner was tired out by always getting the same answer.
When he arrived at <persName id="#man's_estate">man's estate</persName>, he strengthened still more his affection to <persName id="#his_brother">his brother</persName>; for when he was twenty years of age he never supped, he never went abroad, never came into the Forum without <persName id="#caepio">Caepio</persName>.
When <persName id="#caepio">Caepio</persName> used perfumes, <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> would not have them; and in all other respects he was strict and frugal in his way of living.
Accordingly <persName id="#caepio">Caepio</persName>, who was admired for his temperance and moderation, admitted that he was indeed temperate and moderate when contrasted with others, "but," said he, "when I compare my life with <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName>'s, I seem to myself to differ not at all from Sippius;" which was the name of <persName id="#a_man">a man</persName> notorious at that time for luxury and effeminacy.
IV.
After <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> obtained the priesthood of Apollo, he changed his residence, and taking his portion of his paternal property, which portion was a hundred and twenty talents, he contracted his style of living still further, and making <persName id="#his_companion">his companion</persName> of <persName id="#antipater_of_tyrus">Antipater of Tyrus</persName>, a Stoic, he attached himself mainly to Ethical and Political studies, occupying himself with every virtue as if he were possessed by some divine influence; but above all that part of the beautiful which consists in steady adherence to justice and in inflexibility towards partiality or favour was his great delight.
He disciplined himself also in the kind of speaking which works upon numbers, considering that, as in a great state, so in political philosophy, there should be nurtured with it something of the contentious quality.
Yet he did not practise his exercises in <persName id="#company">company</persName> with others, nor did any one hear him when he was declaiming; but to one of <persName id="#his_companions">his companions</persName> who observed, "<persName id="#men">Men</persName> find fault, <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName>, with your silence," he replied, "I only hope they may not find fault with my life.
But I will begin to speak, when I am not going to say something that were better unsaid."
V.
The <placeName id="#basilica">Basilica</placeName> called <personGrp id="#porcia">Porcia</personGrp> was a censorial dedication of the old <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName>.
Now, as <persName id="#the_tribunes">the tribunes</persName> were accustomed to transact business here, and there was a pillar which was considered to be in the way of their seats, they resolved to take it away or to remove it to another spot.
This was the first occasion that brought <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> into the Forum, and against his will; for he opposed <persName id="#the_tribunes">the tribunes</persName>, and he gained admiration by this sample of his eloquence and elevated character.
His speech contained nothing juvenile or artificial, but it was straightforward, full to overflowing, and rough.
However there was diffused over the roughness of the sentiments a charm which led the ear, and his own character intermingled with it gave to the dignity of his address a certain pleasingness and placidity, that were not ill calculated to win <persName id="#men's_favour">men's favour</persName>.
His voice was loud and powerful enough to reach to <persName id="#so_large_a_multitude">so large a multitude</persName>, and it had a strength and tone which could neither be broken nor tired; for he often spoke for a whole day without being wearied.
On this occasion he got the better in the matter in dispute, and then again wrapped himself up in silence and his discipline.
He used to harden his body by vigorous exercises, training himself to endure both heat and snow with uncovered head, and to walk along the roads in all seasons without a vehicle.
<persName id="#his_friends">His friends</persName> who used to accompany him on his journeys employed horses, and Cato would often go side by side with each of them in turns, and talk to them, himself walking while they rode.
He showed in his complaints also wonderful endurance and self-denial; for when he had a fever, he would spend the day quite alone without permitting <persName id="#any_person">any person</persName> to approach him, until he felt certain relief, and that the disease was going away.
VI.
At entertainments he used to cast lots for the parts, and if he failed, and <persName id="#his_friends">his friends</persName> urged him to begin first, he would say that it was not right to do so against the will of <placeName id="#venus">Venus</placeName>.
And at first he would get up from supper after drinking once, but in course of time he stuck to drinking more than <persName id="#anybody">anybody</persName>, so that he often continued over his wine till daybreak.
<persName id="#his_friends">His friends</persName> said that the cause of this was the administration and public affairs, in which <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> being engaged all day and hindered from literary pursuits, associated with <persName id="#philosophers">philosophers</persName> during the night and over his cups.
Accordingly when one <personGrp id="#memmius">Memmius</personGrp> observed in <persName id="#company">company</persName> that <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> was intoxicated all night long, <persName id="#cicero">Cicero</persName> rejoined, "But you do not say that he also plays at dice all day long."
Altogether <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> thought that he ought to walk a course the opposite to the then modes of life and usages, which he considered to be bad and to require a great change, and observing that a purple dress of a deep bright was much in fashion, he himself wore the dark.
He would go into <persName id="#public">public</persName> without shoes and tunic after dinner, not seeking for reputation by the strangeness of the practice, but habituating himself to be ashamed only of what was shameful, and to despise everything else as indifferent.
The inheritance of <persName id="#his_cousin">his cousin</persName> <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> of the value of a hundred talents having been added to his property, he turned it into money and let any of <persName id="#his_friends">his friends</persName> make use of it who needed, without paying interest.
Some also pledged to the treasury both lands and <persName id="#slaves">slaves</persName> of his, which <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> himself offered for this purpose and confirmed the pledge.
VII.
When he considered that he was ripe for marriage, without ever having had to do with <persName id="#any_woman">any woman</persName>, he betrothed <persName id="#lepida">Lepida</persName>, who had before been promised in marriage to <persName id="#scipio_metellus">Scipio Metellus</persName>, but at that time was disengaged, for <persName id="#scipio">Scipio</persName> had repudiated her, and the betrothment was cancelled.
However before the marriage <persName id="#scipio">Scipio</persName> again changed his mind, and by using every exertion got <persName id="#the_maid">the maid</persName>.
Cato, who was greatly irritated and stung, made preparation to prosecute the matter in legal form, but on <persName id="#his_friends">his friends</persName> preventing him, in his passion and youthful fervour he betook himself to iambic verses and vented much injurious language upon <persName id="#scipio">Scipio</persName>, employing the bitterness of <persName id="#archilochus">Archilochus</persName>, but dropping his ungoverned licence and childish manner.
He married <persName id="#atilia">Atilia</persName>, <persName id="#the_daughter">the daughter</persName> of <personGrp id="#soranus">Soranus</personGrp>, and this was <persName id="#the_first_woman">the first woman</persName> with whom he came together, but <persName id="#not_the_only_woman">not the only woman</persName>, like <persName id="#laelius">Laelius</persName> <persName id="#the_companion">the companion</persName> of <persName id="#scipio">Scipio</persName>; for <persName id="#laelius">Laelius</persName> was more fortunate in having known during <persName id="#his_long_life_only_one_woman">his long life only one woman</persName> and <persName id="#that_his_wife">that his wife</persName>.
VIII.
When the Servile War was on foot, which they called the war of Spartacus, Gellius was <persName id="#commander">commander</persName>, but <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> joined the service as <persName id="#a_volunteer">a volunteer</persName> for <persName id="#his_brother's_sake">his brother's sake</persName>, for <persName id="#his_brother">his brother</persName> <persName id="#caepio">Caepio</persName> was <persName id="#a_tribune">a tribune</persName>.
He had not indeed the opportunity of displaying as much as he wished his zeal and his discipline in virtue owing to the war being ill conducted; but notwithstanding this, by showing, in contrast to the great effeminacy and luxury of those who were engaged in that campaign, orderly behaviour and bravery when it was required, and courage and prudence in all things, he was considered in no degree to fall short of the old <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> .
Gellius assigned to him special distinctions and honours, which Cato would not take nor allow, saying that he had done nothing worthy of honour.
In consequence of this he was considered a strange kind of <persName id="#fellow">fellow</persName>; and when a law was made, that those who were <persName id="#candidates">candidates</persName> for an office should not be accompanied by <persName id="#nomenclators">nomenclators</persName>, he was <persName id="#the_only_person">the only person</persName> when a candidate for a tribuneship who observed the law; and having himself made it his business to salute and address those whom he met with, he did not escape censure even from those who praised him, for the more they perceived the honourable nature of his conduct, the more they were annoyed at the difficulty of imitating it.
IX.
Upon being appointed a tribune he was sent to <personGrp id="#macedonia">Macedonia</personGrp> to <personGrp id="#rubrius">Rubrius</personGrp> the Praetor.
On that occasion it is told that <persName id="#his_wife">his wife</persName> being troubled and shedding tears, one of <persName id="#the_friends">the friends</persName> of <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName>, <persName id="#munatius">Munatius</persName>, said, "<persName id="#atilia">Atilia</persName>, be of good cheer; I will take care of him for you."
"It shall be so," replied <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName>; and after they had advanced one day's journey, he said immediately after supper, Come, <persName id="#munatius">Munatius</persName>, and keep your promise to <persName id="#atilia">Atilia</persName> by not separating yourself from me either by day or by night."
Upon this he ordered two beds to be placed in the same chamber and <persName id="#munatius">Munatius</persName> always slept thus, being watched in jest by <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName>.
There accompanied him <persName id="#fifteen_slaves">fifteen slaves</persName>, and <persName id="#two_freedmen">two freedmen</persName> and <persName id="#four_friends">four friends</persName>, and while they rode on horseback, <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> himself always went on foot, keeping by the side of each of them in turns and talking with them.
When he arrived at the camp, where there were <persName id="#several_legions">several legions</persName>, being appointed to the command of <persName id="#one_legion">one legion</persName> by <persName id="#the_general">the general</persName>, he considered the display of his own merit, being only one thing, as a small matter and nothing kingly, but being chiefly ambitious to make those who were under him like himself, he did not deprive his power of its terrors, but he added to it reason, by means of which persuading and instructing <persName id="#his_men">his men</persName> about every thing--honour and punishment following; whether he made <persName id="#his_soldiers">his soldiers</persName> more peaceable or warlike or more full of zeal or just, it is difficult to say, so formidable did they become to <persName id="#the_enemy">the enemy</persName>, and gentle to <persName id="#the_allies">the allies</persName>, and so little disposed to wrong, and so ambitious of praise.
But that which <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> cared least for, he had most of, both good opinion, and popularity, and honour above measure, and affection from <persName id="#the_soldiers">the soldiers</persName>.
For by voluntarily labouring at that which he imposed on others, and in his dress and way of living and marching on foot making himself like them rather than <persName id="#the_commander">the commander</persName>, and in his morals and in his noble bearing, and in eloquence surpassing all who were intitled Imperators and <persName id="#generals">generals</persName>, by such means he imperceptibly produced in <persName id="#the_men">the men</persName> at the same time good will towards himself.
For no true emulation after virtue is bred except from perfect good will and respect towards him who commends it: but those who having no love, praise the brave, respect their character, though they admire not their virtue, nor do they imitate it.
X.
Hearing that Athenodorus named Kordylion, who had great skill in the Stoic philosophy, was living at Pergamus, being now <persName id="#an_old_man">an old man</persName>, and having most resolutely resisted all intimacy and friendship with <persName id="#governors">governors</persName> and <persName id="#kings">kings</persName>, <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> thought that he should get nothing by sending and writing to him, but as he had a furlough of two months allowed by the law, he made a voyage to <placeName id="#asia">Asia</placeName> to <persName id="#the_man">the man</persName>, in the confidence that through his own merits he should not fail in the chase.
After discoursing with Athenodorus and getting the victory over him and drawing him from his settled purpose, he returned with him to the camp, overjoyed and greatly elated at having made the noblest capture and got a more splendid booty than the nations and kingdoms which at that time and were subduing in their campaigns.
XI.
While <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> was still engaged in the service, <persName id="#his_brother">his brother</persName>, who was on his road to <placeName id="#asia">Asia</placeName>, fell sick at <placeName id="#aenus">Aenus</placeName>, in <placeName id="#thrace">Thrace</placeName>; and a letter immediately came to <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName>, and though the sea was very stormy, and there was no vessel at hand of sufficient size, taking <persName id="#only_two_friends">only two friends</persName> with him and <persName id="#three_slaves">three slaves</persName>, he set sail from <personGrp id="#thessalonike">Thessalonike</personGrp> in a small trading ship.
After narrowly escaping being drowned at sea, he was saved by unexpected good luck, but he found <persName id="#caepio">Caepio</persName> already dead.
He was considered to have borne the misfortune with more of passion than philosophy, not only in his lamentations and his embracings of the dead body and the heaviness of his grief, but also in his expenditure about the interment, and the trouble that he took about fragrant spices and costly vests which were burnt with the body, and a monument of polished <personGrp id="#thasian">Thasian</personGrp> stone of the cost of eight talents which was constructed in the Agora of Aenus.
These things there were some who found fault with by comparison with Cato's freedom from all display in other matters, not seeing how much mildness and affection there was in <persName id="#the_man">the man</persName> who was inflexible and firm against pleasures and fears and shameless entreaties.
For the celebration of the funeral both cities and <persName id="#princes">princes</persName> offered to send him many things to do honour to the dead, from none of whom however would he receive valuables, but he accepted fragrant spices and vests, paying the price to those who sent the things.
Though the succession came to him and <persName id="#the_young_daughter">the young daughter</persName> of <persName id="#caepio">Caepio</persName>, he did not claim back in the division of the property any thing that he had expended about the funeral.
And though he did such things as these and continued to do such, there was one who wrote, that he passed the ashes of the dead through a sieve and sifted them to search for the gold that was burnt.
So far did <persName id="#the_writer">the writer</persName> allow, not to his sword only, but also to his stilus, irresponsibility and exemption from all account.
XII.
When the time of <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName>'s service was at an end, he was attended on his departure, not with good wishes, which is usual, nor yet with praises, but with tears and never-satisfied embraces, <persName id="#the_soldiers">the soldiers</persName> placing their garments under his feet on the way by which he went and kissing his hands, which the <personGrp id="#romans">Romans</personGrp> of that day hardly ever did to any of their Imperators.
As he wished, before engaging in public affairs, at the same time to travel about to make himself acquainted with <placeName id="#asia">Asia</placeName>, and to see with his own eyes the customs and mode of living and power of each province, and at the same time not to give any offence to <persName id="#the_galatian_deiotarus">the Galatian Deiotarus</persName>, who prayed <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> to come to him on account of the ancient ties of hospitality and friendship that subsisted between him and <persName id="#cato's_family">Cato's family</persName>, he made his sojourning after this fashion.
At daybreak he used to send forward <persName id="#his_bread-maker">his bread-maker</persName> and cook to the place where he intended to lodge; and it was their practice to enter the city with great decorum and no stir, and if there happened to be <persName id="#no_ancient_friend">no ancient friend</persName> of <persName id="#cato's_family">Cato's family</persName> there or no acquaintance, they would prepare for his reception in an inn without troubling <persName id="#anybody">anybody</persName>; and if there was no inn, they would in that case apply to <persName id="#the_magistrates">the magistrates</persName> and gladly accept what accommodation was offered.
And oftentimes getting no credit, and being neglected because they did not apply to <persName id="#the_magistrates">the magistrates</persName> about these matters with noise or threats, <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> came upon them before they had accomplished their business, and when he was seen, he was still more despised; and because he would sit silently on the baggage, he gave them the notion of being <persName id="#a_person">a person</persName> of mean condition and <persName id="#a_very_timid_man">a very timid man</persName>.
However <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> would call them to him, and would say, "<persName id="#ye_miserable_wretches">Ye miserable wretches</persName>, lay aside this inhospitable practice.
All those who come to you will not be <persName id="#catos">Catos</persName>.
Dull by your kind reception the power of those who only want a pretext to take by force what they cannot get from you with your consent."
XIII.
In <personGrp id="#syria">Syria</personGrp> a laughable incident is said to have happened to him.
For as he was walking to <placeName id="#antiocheia">Antiocheia</placeName>, he saw near the gates on the outside a number of <persName id="#men">men</persName> arranged on each side of the road, among whom <persName id="#young_men">young men</persName> by themselves in cloaks and <persName id="#boys">boys</persName> on the other side stood in orderly wise, and some had white vests and crowns, and these were <persName id="#priests">priests</persName> of <persName id="#the_gods">the gods</persName> or <persName id="#magistrates">magistrates</persName>.
Now <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName>, being quite sure that some honourable reception was preparing for him by the city, was angry with those of <persName id="#his_own_people">his own people</persName> who had been sent on, for not having prevented this, and he bade <persName id="#his_friends">his friends</persName> get off their horses and he proceeded with them on foot.
But when they came near, he who was arranging all this ceremony and setting <persName id="#the_folk">the folk</persName> in order, <persName id="#a_man">a man</persName> somewhat advanced in years, holding a rod in his hand and a chaplet, advanced in front of the rest, and meeting <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName>, without even saluting him, asked where they had left <persName id="#demetrius">Demetrius</persName> and when he would be there.
<persName id="#demetrius">Demetrius</persName> had been <persName id="#a_slave">a slave</persName> of <persName id="#pompeius">Pompeius</persName>, but at this time, as all the world, so to speak, had their eyes on <persName id="#pompeius">Pompeius</persName>, <persName id="#demetrius">Demetrius</persName> was courted above his merits on account of his great influence with <persName id="#pompeius">Pompeius</persName>.
Now <persName id="#the_friends">the friends</persName> of <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> were seized with such a fit of laughter that they could not contain themselves as they walked through the crowd, but <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName>, who at the time was vehemently disconcerted, uttered the words, "O ill-fated city," and nothing more; afterwards however he was accustomed to laugh at the matter himself both when he told the story and when he thought of it.
XIV.
However <persName id="#pompeius">Pompeius</persName> himself reproved those who thus misbehaved themselves towards <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> in their ignorance.
For when <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> on his arrival at <placeName id="#ephesus">Ephesus</placeName> went to pay his respects to <persName id="#pompeius">Pompeius</persName> as <persName id="#his_elder">his elder</persName>, and much his superior in reputation and then at the head of <persName id="#the_greatest_armies">the greatest armies</persName>, <persName id="#pompeius">Pompeius</persName> observing him did not wait or allow <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> to approach him as he was seated, but springing up as to <persName id="#a_man">a man</persName> of superior rank, he met him and gave him his right hand.
And <persName id="#pompeius">Pompeius</persName> passed many encomiums on the merit of Cato while treating him as <persName id="#a_friend">a friend</persName> and showing him attention during his stay, and still more when he had departed, so that all persons being admonished and now directing their observation to <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> admired him for the things for which he was despised, and studied his mildness and magnanimity.
Yet it did not escape notice that the great attention of Pompeius to him proceeded more from respect than from love, and <persName id="#people">people</persName> discerned that <persName id="#pompeius">Pompeius</persName> honoured him while he was present, and was glad when he went away.
For <persName id="#the_other_young_men">the other young men</persName> who came to him, he was ambitious to keep with him, and he wished them to stay, but he asked of <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> nothing of the kind, and as if he were not <persName id="#commander">commander</persName> with irresponsible power while <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> was there, he was glad to get rid of him; and yet he was <persName id="#almost_the_only_person">almost the only person</persName> among those who were sailing to <personGrp id="#rome">Rome</personGrp> to whom <persName id="#pompeius">Pompeius</persName> commended <persName id="#his_children">his children</persName> and <persName id="#wife">wife</persName>, who however were connected with Cato by kinship.
In consequence of this there was high regard and great exertion and emulation in the cities towards Cato, and suppers and invitations, wherein Cato bade <persName id="#his_friends">his friends</persName> keep a watch upon him, lest he should unawares make good what Curio had said.
For Curio, who was annoyed at the austerity of <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName>, who was <persName id="#his_friend">his friend</persName> and intimate, asked him if he should like to visit <placeName id="#asia">Asia</placeName> after he had served his time in <persName id="#the_army">the army</persName>.
And on <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> saying that he should like it very much, "You say well," replied <persName id="#curio">Curio</persName>, "for you will be more agreeable when you return thence, and tamer," using some such words as these.
XV.
Deiotarus the Galatian, who was now <persName id="#an_old_man">an old man</persName>, sent for <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName>, wishing to intrust to him <persName id="#his_children">his children</persName> and <persName id="#his_family_deiotarus'_family">his family Deiotarus' family</persName>; and on his arrival he offered him all manner of presents, and tried and entreated him in every way till he so irritated <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName>, that after arriving in the evening and staying all night, he set off on the following day about the third hour.
However when he had advanced one day's journey, he found in <personGrp id="#possinus">Possinus</personGrp> more presents than before awaiting him there, and letters from the <persName id="#galatian">Galatian</persName> begging him to receive them; and if he should not be disposed to take them, to let <persName id="#his_friends">his friends</persName> at least receive favours on his account, as they well deserved it, and Cato had not much of his own.
But Cato did not give in even to these arguments, though he saw that some of <persName id="#his_friends">his friends</persName> were beginning to be softened and were inclined to blame him; but observing that all receiving of gifts might find a good excuse, and <persName id="#his_friends">his friends</persName> should share in all that he got honourably and justly, he sent back the presents to Deiotarus.
As he was about to set sail to Brundisium, <persName id="#his_friends">his friends</persName> thought that they ought to put the ashes of <persName id="#caepio">Caepio</persName> in another vessel, but <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName>, saying that he would rather part with his life than the ashes of <persName id="#his_brother">his brother</persName>, set sail.
And indeed it is said that it chanced that he had a very dangerous passage, though the rest got to Brundisium with little difficulty.
XVI.
On his return to <personGrp id="#rome">Rome</personGrp> he spent his time either at home in <persName id="#the_company">the company</persName> of Athenodorus, or in the Forum assisting <persName id="#his_friends">his friends</persName>.
Though the office of <persName id="#quaestor">Quaestor</persName> was now open to him, he did not become <persName id="#a_candidate">a candidate</persName> for it till he had read the laws relating to the quaestorship, and had learned all particulars from the experienced, and had comprehended the powers of the office in a certain shape.
Accordingly as soon as he was established in the office, he made a great change in <persName id="#the_servants">the servants</persName> and <persName id="#clerks">clerks</persName> about the treasury, for as they constantly had in hand the public accounts and the laws, and had <persName id="#young_superiors">young superiors</persName> who, by reason of their inexperience and ignorance, in fact required others to teach and direct them, they did not allow <persName id="#their_superiors">their superiors</persName> to have any power, but were <persName id="#the_superior_officers">the superior officers</persName> themselves, until <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> vigorously applied himself to the business, not having the name only and the honour of <persName id="#a_magistrate">a magistrate</persName>, but understanding and judgment and apt expression; and he resolved to make <persName id="#the_clerks">the clerks</persName> into <persName id="#servants">servants</persName> as they really were, in some things detecting their evil doings, and in others correcting their errors which arose from inexperience.
But as <persName id="#the_clerks">the clerks</persName> were insolent, and attempted to ingratiate themselves with and to flatter <persName id="#the_other_quaestors">the other quaestors</persName>, and resisted him, he expelled from the treasury the first among them whom he had detected in knavish dealings in a matter of trust concerning an inheritance, and he brought another to trial for dishonesty.
<persName id="#this_second_person">This second person</persName> <persName id="#catulus_lutatius">Catulus Lutatius</persName> <persName id="#the_censor">the censor</persName> came forward to defend, <persName id="#a_man">a man</persName> who had great dignity from his office, and the greatest from his merit, being considered superior to all the <personGrp id="#romans">Romans</personGrp> in integrity and temperance; and he was also <persName id="#an_admirer">an admirer</persName> and <persName id="#intimate_friend">intimate friend</persName> of <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> all through his life.
Now, when Catulus found that the justice of the case was against him and openly asked to have <persName id="#the_man">the man</persName> acquitted for his sake, <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> would not allow him to act so: and when he still continued to urge his request, Cato said, "It were a scandalous thing, <persName id="#catulus">Catulus</persName>, for you, who are <persName id="#the_censor">the censor</persName>, and whose duty it is to examine into our lives, to be turned out by <persName id="#our_officers">our officers</persName>."
When <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> had uttered these words, <persName id="#catulus">Catulus</persName> looked at him as if he were going to reply, but he said nothing, and either being angry or ashamed he went away in silence and perplexed.
However <persName id="#the_man">the man</persName> was not convicted, for when the votes for condemnation had exceeded those for acquittal by a single vote, and <persName id="#lollius_marcus">Lollius Marcus</persName>, one of <persName id="#the_colleagues">the colleagues</persName> of Cato, owing to sickness had not attended at the trial, <persName id="#catulus">Catulus</persName> sent to him and prayed him to give his support to <persName id="#the_man">the man</persName>; and he was carried thither in a litter after the trial and gave the vote which acquitted.
However <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> did not employ <persName id="#the_clerk">the clerk</persName> nor give him his pay, nor did he take any reckoning at all of the vote of <persName id="#lollius">Lollius</persName>.
XVII.
Having thus humbled <persName id="#the_clerks">the clerks</persName> and reduced them to obedience, by managing the accounts in his own way, he made the treasury in a short time more respected than the Senate, so that every body said and considered that <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> had surrounded the quaestorship with the dignity of the consulship.
For in the first place finding that many persons owed old debts to the state and that the state was indebted to many, he at the same time put an end to the state being wronged and wronging others, by demanding the money from those who owed it vigorously and without relenting at all, and paying <persName id="#the_creditors">the creditors</persName> speedily and readily, so that <persName id="#the_people">the people</persName> respected him when they saw those pay who expected to defraud the state, and those recover who never expected it.
In the next place, it was the general practice to bring in writings without observing the proper forms, and <persName id="#previous_quaestors">previous quaestors</persName> used to receive false decrees to please persons, and at their request.
Cato however let nothing of this kind escape his notice, and on one occasion being in doubt about a decree, whether it was really ratified, though many persons testified to the fact, he would not trust them, nor did he allow it to be deposited until <persName id="#the_consuls">the consuls</persName> came and by oath confirmed its genuineness.
Now there were many whom <persName id="#sulla">Sulla</persName> had rewarded for killing proscribed persons at the rate of twelve thousand drachmae apiece, and though all detested them as <persName id="#accursed_and_abominable_wretches">accursed and abominable wretches</persName>, no one ventured to bring them to punishment; but <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName>, calling to account <persName id="#every_man">every man</persName> who had public money by unfair means, made him give it up and at the same time upbraided him for his unholy and illegal acts with passion and argument.
Those whom this befel were immediately charged with murder and were brought before <persName id="#the_judices">the judices</persName> in a manner prejudged, and were punished, to the joy of all who considered that the tyranny of those former times was at the same time blotted out and that they witnessed <persName id="#sulla">Sulla</persName> himself punished.
XVIII.
The many were captivated by his persevering and unwearied industry: for none of <persName id="#his_colleagues">his colleagues</persName> went up earlier to the treasury or came away after him.
He never omitted attending any meeting of <persName id="#the_people">the people</persName> and of the Senate, for he feared and kept a watch on those who were ready to vote for remissions of debts and taxes and for gifts in favour of any body.
By proving that the treasury was inaccessible and free from intrigues, and full of money, he showed that they could be rich without doing wrong.
Though at first he appeared to be disliked by and odious to some of <persName id="#his_colleagues">his colleagues</persName>, he afterwards gained their good-will by subjecting himself on behalf of them all to the hatred that was incurred by not giving away the public money and by not deciding dishonestly, and by furnishing them with an answer to those who preferred their requests and urged them, that nothing could be done if <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> did not consent.
On the last day of his office when he had been accompanied to his house by <persName id="#almost_all_the_citizens">almost all the citizens</persName>, he heard that many who were intimate with <persName id="#marcellus">Marcellus</persName>, and <persName id="#men">men</persName> of influence, had fallen upon him at the treasury and having got round him were forcing him to sign a certain payment of money that was due.
<persName id="#marcellus">Marcellus</persName> from his boyhood had been <persName id="#a_friend">a friend</persName> of <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> and together with him had been <persName id="#a_most_excellent_magistrate">a most excellent magistrate</persName>, but by himself he was easily led by others through false shame, and was ready to oblige any body.
Accordingly <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> immediately returned to the treasury, and finding that <persName id="#marcellus">Marcellus</persName> had been prevailed upon to sign the payment asked for the tablets and erased what was written, while <persName id="#marcellus">Marcellus</persName> stood by and said not a word.
Having done this <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> conducted him down from the treasury and put him in his house; and <persName id="#marcellus">Marcellus</persName> neither then nor afterwards found fault with <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName>, but continued on intimate terms with him all along.
Nor did <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> when he had quitted the treasury leave it destitute of protection, but <persName id="#slaves">slaves</persName> of his were there daily who copied out the transactions, and he himself purchased for five talents books which contained the public accounts from the times of <persName id="#sulla">Sulla</persName> to his own quaestorship, and he always had them in his hands.
XIX.
He used to go into the Senate house the first, and he was the last to come away; and often while the rest were slowly assembling, he would sit and read quietly, holding his toga before the book.
He never went abroad when there was to be a meeting of the Senate; but afterwards when <persName id="#pompeius">Pompeius</persName> saw that <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> could not be prevailed upon, and could never be brought to comply with the unjust measures on which he was intent, he used to contrive to engage him in giving his aid to <persName id="#some_friend">some friend</persName> in a matter before the courts, or in arbitrations, or in discharging some business.
But <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> quickly perceiving his design, refused all such engagements and made it a rule to do nothing else while the Senate was assembled.
For it was neither for the sake of reputation, nor self-aggrandisement, nor by a kind of spontaneous movement, nor by chance, like some others, that he was thrown into the management of state affairs, but he selected a public career as the proper labour of <persName id="#a_good_man">a good man</persName>, and thought that he ought to attend to public concerns more than the bee to its cells, inasmuch as he made it his business to have the affairs of the provinces and decrees and trials and the most important measures communicated to him by his connections and <persName id="#friends">friends</persName> in every place.
On one occasion by opposing <persName id="#clodius">Clodius</persName> <persName id="#the_demagogue">the demagogue</persName>, who was making a disturbance and laying the foundation for great charges, and calumniating to <persName id="#the_people">the people</persName> <persName id="#the_priests">the priests</persName> and <persName id="#priestesses">priestesses</persName>, among whom was also <persName id="#fabia">Fabia</persName>, <persName id="#the_sister">the sister</persName> of Terentia, <persName id="#cicero's_wife">Cicero's wife</persName>, he was in great danger, but he involved Clodius in disgrace and compelled him to withdraw from the city; and when <persName id="#cicero">Cicero</persName> thanked him, <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> said that he ought to reserve his gratitude for the state, as it was for the sake of the state that he did every thing and directed his political measures.
In consequence of this there was a high opinion of him, so that <persName id="#an_orator">an orator</persName> said to <persName id="#the_judices">the judices</persName> on a certain trial when the evidence of <persName id="#a_single_person">a single person</persName> was produced, that it was not right to believe <persName id="#a_single_witness">a single witness</persName> even if he was <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName>; and many persons now were used to say when speaking of things incredible and contrary to all probability, as by way of proverb, that this could not be believed even if <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> said it.
And when <persName id="#a_man">a man</persName> of bad character and great expense delivered a discourse in <persName id="#the_senate">the senate</persName> in favour of frugality and temperance, Amnaeus rose up and said, "My man, who will endure you, you who sup like <personGrp id="#crassus">Crassus</personGrp>, and build like <personGrp id="#lucullus">Lucullus</personGrp>, and harangue us like <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName>."
Others also who were <persName id="#people">people</persName> of bad character and intemperate, but in their language dignified and severe, they used to call by way of mockery, <persName id="#catos">Catos</persName>.
XX.
Though many invited him to the tribuneship, he did not think it well to expend the power of a great office and magistracy, no more than that of a strong medicine, on matters wherein it was not required.
At the same time as he had leisure from public affairs, he took books and <persName id="#philosophers">philosophers</persName> with him and set out for Lucania, for he had lands there on which there was no unseemly residence.
On the road he met with many beasts of burden and baggage and <persName id="#slaves">slaves</persName>, and learning that Nepos Metellus was returning to <personGrp id="#rome">Rome</personGrp> for the purpose of being <persName id="#a_candidate">a candidate</persName> for the tribuneship, he halted without speaking, and after a short interval ordered <persName id="#his_people">his people</persName> to turn back.
<persName id="#his_friends">His friends</persName> wondering at this, he said, "Don't you know that even of himself Metellus is <persName id="#a_formidable_man">a formidable man</persName> by reason of his violence; and now that he has come upon the motion of <persName id="#pompeius">Pompeius</persName>, he will fall upon the state like a thunderbolt and put all in confusion? It is therefore not a time for leisure or going from home, but we must get the better of <persName id="#the_man">the man</persName> or die nobly in defence of liberty."
However at the urgency of <persName id="#his_friends">his friends</persName> he went first to visit his estates, and after staying no long time he returned to the city.
He arrived in the evening, and as soon as day dawned, he went down into the Forum to be <persName id="#a_candidate">a candidate</persName> for the tribuneship and to oppose Metellus.
For this magistracy gives more power to check than to act; and even if all the rest of <persName id="#the_tribunes">the tribunes</persName> save one should assent to a measure, the power lies with him who does not consent or permit.
XXI.
At first there were few of <persName id="#cato's_friends">Cato's friends</persName> about him, but when his views became public, in a short time <persName id="#all_the_people">all the people</persName> of character and distinction crowded together and cheered and encouraged him, for they said it was no favour that he was receiving, but he was conferring the greatest favour on his country and the most honest of <persName id="#the_citizens">the citizens</persName>, for that when it was often in his power to hold a magistracy without any trouble, he now came down to contend on behalf of freedom and the constitution, not without danger.
It is said that owing to many persons through zeal and friendly disposition crowding towards him he was in some danger, and with difficulty on account of the crowd he made his way to the Forum.
Being elected tribune with others and with Metellus, and observing that the consular comitia were accompanied with bribery, he rated <persName id="#the_people">the people</persName>, and at the close of his speech he swore that he would prosecute <persName id="#the_briber">the briber</persName>, <persName id="#whoever">whoever</persName> he might be, with the exception of <placeName id="#silanus">Silanus</placeName>, on account of his connection with him; for <persName id="#silanus">Silanus</persName> had to wife Servilia, <persName id="#a_sister">a sister</persName> of <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName>.
For this reason he passed over <persName id="#silanus">Silanus</persName>, but he prosecuted <persName id="#lucius_murena">Lucius Murena</persName>, on the charge of having secured his election with <persName id="#silanus">Silanus</persName> by bribery.
There was a law according to which the accused had always the power to appoint <persName id="#a_person">a person</persName> to watch <persName id="#the_accuser">the accuser</persName>, in order that it might not be unknown what he was getting together and preparing to support the prosecution.
Now he who was appointed by <persName id="#murena">Murena</persName> to watch <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> used to accompany him and observe his conduct, and when he saw that <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> was doing nothing with unfair design or contrary to equity, but honourably and in a kindly spirit was going a simple and straightforward course towards the prosecution, he had such admiration of his noble bearing and morality that he would come up to <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> in the Forum, or go to his door and ask, whether he intended that day to attend to any matters that concerned the prosecution, and if he said that he did not, he would take his word and go away.
When the trial came on, Cicero, who was then <persName id="#consul">consul</persName> and one of <persName id="#the_advocates">the advocates</persName> of <personGrp id="#murena">Murena</personGrp>, on account of Cato's connection with the Stoics, ridiculed and mocked <persName id="#these_philosophers">these philosophers</persName> and their so-called paradoxes, and thus made <persName id="#the_judices">the judices</persName> laugh.
On which it is said that <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName>, with a smile, observed to those who were present, "My friends, <persName id="#what_a_ridiculous_consul">what a ridiculous consul</persName> we have."
<personGrp id="#murena">Murena</personGrp>, who was acquitted, did not display towards <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> the temper of a bad or <persName id="#a_foolish_man">a foolish man</persName>, for in his consulship he used to ask his advice in the most important affairs, and all along in every other matter showed him respect and confidence.
<persName id="#cato">Cato</persName>'s own conduct was the cause of this, for while he was severe and terrible on the judgment seat and in the Senate on behalf of justice, he was benevolent and friendly in all his social intercourse.
XXII.
Before <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> entered on the tribuneship, during Cicero's consulship he supported his administration in many other difficulties, and he put the finishing stroke to the measures relating to Catiline, which were the most important and glorious of all.
Catiline himself, who was designing to effect a pernicious and complete change in the <personGrp id="#roman">Roman</personGrp> state, and was at the same time stirring up insurrection and war, being convicted by Cicero, fled from the city; but Lentulus and <personGrp id="#cethegus">Cethegus</personGrp> and many others with them, who had taken up the conspiracy, upbraiding <persName id="#catiline">Catiline</persName> with cowardice and want of spirit in his designs, were plotting to destroy the city with fire, and to subvert the supremacy of <personGrp id="#rome">Rome</personGrp> by the revolt of nations and by foreign wars.
Their schemes having been discovered in the manner told in the Life of Cicero, he laid the matter before the Senate for their deliberation, whereupon Silanus, who spoke first, gave his opinion that <persName id="#the_men">the men</persName> ought to suffer the extreme punishment, and those who followed him spoke to the same effect, till it came to <persName id="#caesar">Caesar</persName>'s turn.
Caesar now rose, and as he was <persName id="#a_powerful_speaker">a powerful speaker</persName> and wished rather to increase all change and disturbance in the state than to allow it to be quenched, considering it as the stuff for his own designs to work upon, he urged many arguments of a persuasive and humane kind to the effect that <persName id="#the_men">the men</persName> ought not to be put to death without trial, and he advised that they should be confined in prison: and he wrought so great a change in the opinion of the Senate, who were afraid of <persName id="#the_people">the people</persName>, that even <persName id="#silanus">Silanus</persName> retracted what he had said, and affirmed that neither had he recommended that they should be put to death, but that they should be imprisoned; for to a <personGrp id="#roman">Roman</personGrp> this was the extreme of punishment.
XXIII.
Such had been the change, and all the Senators in a body had gone over to the milder and more humane proposal, when <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> rising to deliver his opinion, commenced his speech in anger and passion, abusing <persName id="#silanus">Silanus</persName> for changing his mind, and attacking <persName id="#caesar">Caesar</persName>, whom he charged with a design to overturn the State under <persName id="#a_popular_guise">a popular guise</persName> and pretext of humanity, and with making the Senate alarmed at things at which he himself ought to be alarmed, and therewith well content, if he escaped unharmed on account of what had passed and without suspicion, when he was so openly and audaciously endeavouring to rescue <persName id="#the_common_enemies">the common enemies</persName> of all, and admitting that he had no pity for the state, such and so great though it was, and though it had so narrowly escaped destruction, but was shedding tears and lamenting because those who ought never to have existed or been born would by their death release the state from great bloodshed and danger.
They say that this is the only speech of Cato which is preserved, and that it was owing to Cicero <persName id="#the_consul">the consul</persName>, who had previously instructed <persName id="#those_clerks">those clerks</persName> who surpassed the rest in quick writing in the use of certain signs which comprehended in their small and brief marks the force of many characters and had placed them in different parts of the Senate house.
For the <personGrp id="#romans">Romans</personGrp> at this time were not used to employ nor did they possess what are called note-writers, but it was on this occasion, as they say, that they were first established in a certain form.
However, <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> prevailed and changed the opinion of the Senate, who condemned <persName id="#the_men">the men</persName> to death.
XXIV.
Now as we perhaps ought not to omit even the slight tokens of character when we are delineating as it were a likeness of the soul, it is reported that on this occasion when <persName id="#caesar">Caesar</persName> was making much exertion and a great struggle against <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName>, and the attention of the Senate was fixed on both of them, a small letter was brought in for Caesar from the outside.
<persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> attempted to fix suspicion on this matter, and alleged that some of <persName id="#the_senators">the senators</persName> were disturbed at it and he bade him read the writing, on which Caesar handed the letter to <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> who was standing near him.
Cato read the letter, which was an amatory epistle addressed to <persName id="#caesar">Caesar</persName> by <persName id="#his_sister">his sister</persName> Servilia who was enamoured of <persName id="#caesar">Caesar</persName> and had been debauched by him, and throwing it at <persName id="#caesar">Caesar</persName> he said, "Take it, drunkard," and so resumed his speech.
Indeed in the female part of <persName id="#his_family">his family</persName> <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> appears to have always been unlucky.
For <persName id="#this_sister">this sister</persName> had a bad report in respect of <persName id="#caesar">Caesar</persName>; and the conduct of the other <personGrp id="#servilia">Servilia</personGrp>, <persName id="#also_a_sister">also a sister</persName> of <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName>, was still more unseemly.
For though she was married to Lucullus, <persName id="#a_man">a man</persName> who was among the first of the <personGrp id="#romans">Romans</personGrp> in reputation, and bore him <persName id="#a_child">a child</persName>, she was driven from his house for incontinence.
And what was most scandalous of all, even <persName id="#cato's_wife">Cato's wife</persName> <persName id="#atilia">Atilia</persName> was not free from such vices, for though he had <persName id="#two_children">two children</persName> by her, he was compelled to put her away for her unseemly behaviour.
XXV.
Cato then married <persName id="#marcia">Marcia</persName>, <persName id="#a_daughter">a daughter</persName> of <persName id="#philippus">Philippus</persName>, who had the character of being <persName id="#an_honest_woman">an honest woman</persName>, and about whom a good deal is said; but just as in a drama, this part of Cato's life is a difficult and perplexed matter.
However it was after the following manner, as <persName id="#thrasea">Thrasea</persName> writes, who refers as his authority to <persName id="#munatius">Munatius</persName>, <persName id="#a_companion">a companion</persName> and <persName id="#intimate_associate">intimate associate</persName> of <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName>.
Among <persName id="#the_numerous_friends">the numerous friends</persName> and <persName id="#admirers">admirers</persName> of Cato there were some more conspicuous and distinguished than others, of whom one was <persName id="#quintus_hortensius">Quintus Hortensius</persName>, <persName id="#a_man">a man</persName> of splendid reputation and honest morals.
Now as <persName id="#hortensius">Hortensius</persName> was desirous to be not merely <persName id="#an_intimate_friend">an intimate friend</persName> and <persName id="#companion">companion</persName> of <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName>, but in a manner to unite in kinship and community <persName id="#the_whole_family">the whole family</persName> and stock, he endeavoured to persuade <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName>, <persName id="#whose_daughter">whose daughter</persName> <persName id="#porcia">Porcia</persName> was <persName id="#the_wife">the wife</persName> of <personGrp id="#bibulus">Bibulus</personGrp> and had born him <persName id="#two_sons">two sons</persName>, to give her in turn to him as a fertile soil to beget <persName id="#children">children</persName> in.
He said that according to <persName id="#men's_opinion">men's opinion</persName> such a thing was strange, but that according to nature it was good and for the advantage of states, that <persName id="#a_woman">a woman</persName> who was in <persName id="#her_youth">her youth</persName> and perfection should neither lie idle and check her procreative power, nor yet should by breeding <persName id="#more_children">more children</persName> than enough cause trouble to <persName id="#her_husband">her husband</persName> and impoverish him when he wanted <persName id="#no_more_children">no more children</persName>; but that if there was a community of offspring among <persName id="#worthy_men">worthy men</persName>, it would make virtue abundant and widely diffused among <persName id="#families">families</persName>, and would mingle the state with itself by <persName id="#these_family_relationships">these family relationships</persName>.
If <personGrp id="#bibulus">Bibulus</personGrp>, he said, was greatly attached to <persName id="#his_wife">his wife</persName>, he would return her as soon as she had born <persName id="#a_child">a child</persName>, and he had become more closely united both with <personGrp id="#bibulus">Bibulus</personGrp> and <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> by a community of <persName id="#children">children</persName>.
<persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> replied that he loved Hortensius and valued his kinship, but he considered it strange for Hortensius to speak about the marriage of <persName id="#his_daughter">his daughter</persName> who had been given to another; on which Hortensius changing his proposal and disclosing himself did not hesitate to ask <persName id="#the_wife">the wife</persName> of <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName>, who was still young enough to bear <persName id="#children">children</persName>, while <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> himself had <persName id="#children">children</persName> enough.
And it cannot be said that Hortensius did this because he knew that <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> paid no attention to <persName id="#marcia">Marcia</persName>, for they say that she happened to be with <persName id="#child">child</persName> at the time.
Accordingly <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> seeing the earnestness and eagerness of Hortensius did not refuse, but he said that <persName id="#philippus">Philippus</persName> <persName id="#the_father">the father</persName> of <persName id="#marcia">Marcia</persName> must also approve of it.
When they had seen <persName id="#philippus">Philippus</persName> and informed him of the agreement, he did not give <persName id="#marcia">Marcia</persName> in marriage, except in the presence of <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName>, and Cato joined in giving her away.
Though this took place later, it seemed convenient to me to anticipate the time as I had made mention of the female part of <persName id="#cato's_family">Cato's family</persName>.
XXVI.
When Lentulus and <persName id="#his_associates">his associates</persName> had been executed, and <persName id="#caesar">Caesar</persName>, on account of the charges and insinuations made against him before the Senate, betook himself to <persName id="#the_people">the people</persName> for protection and was stirring up <persName id="#the_numerous_diseased_and_corrupted_members">the numerous diseased and corrupted members</persName> of the state and collecting them about him, Cato, being alarmed, persuaded the Senate to relieve the crowd of poor who had no property by an allowance of grain, the expenditure for which purpose was to the amount of twelve hundred and fifty talents annually; and the threats of <persName id="#caesar">Caesar</persName> were manifestly rendered futile by this liberality and bounty.
After this, <persName id="#metellus">Metellus</persName>, as soon as he had entered on the tribuneship, got together tumultuous meetings and proposed a law that <persName id="#pompeius_magnus">Pompeius Magnus</persName> should hasten to <personGrp id="#italy">Italy</personGrp> with his forces and should undertake the protection of the city, which it was alleged was in danger from Catiline.
This was in appearance a specious proposal, but the real object and end of the law was to put affairs in the hands of Pompeius and to surrender to him the supremacy.
When the Senate was assembled and Cato did not in his usual way fall violently on Metellus, but advised him with much forbearance and moderation, and at last even betook himself to entreaty and praised <persName id="#the_family">the family</persName> of the <persName id="#metelli">Metelli</persName> for having always been aristocratic, <persName id="#metellus">Metellus</persName> becoming much emboldened and despising <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName>, whom he supposed to be giving way and cowering, broke out in extravagant threats and arrogant expressions, as if he would accomplish every thing in spite of the Senate.
On this Cato, changing his attitude and tone and language, and concluding all that he said with a vehement affirmation that so long as he lived Pompeius should not come into the city with <persName id="#his_soldiers">his soldiers</persName>, brought the Senate to this opinion, that neither he nor Metellus was in a sober mind and that neither of them was guided by sound considerations, but that the measures of Metellus were madness which from excess of depravity was loading to the destruction and confusion of every thing, and those of <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> an enthusiasm of virtue struggling in behalf of honour and justice.
XXVII.
But when <persName id="#the_people">the people</persName> were going to vote on the law, and <persName id="#armed_strangers">armed strangers</persName> and <persName id="#gladiators">gladiators</persName> and <persName id="#slaves">slaves</persName> had come to the Forum arrayed to support Metellus, and that part of <persName id="#the_people">the people</persName> which longed for <persName id="#pompeius">Pompeius</persName> from desire of change was not small, and there was also great support from <persName id="#caesar">Caesar</persName> who was then <persName id="#praetor">praetor</persName>, and <persName id="#the_first_men">the first men</persName> of <persName id="#the_citizens">the citizens</persName> rather shared in the indignation and wrongs of <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> than joined him in making resistance, and great depression and alarm prevailed in <persName id="#his_family">his family</persName>, so that some of <persName id="#his_friends">his friends</persName> taking no food watched all night with one another in perplexed deliberation on his behalf, and <persName id="#his_wife">his wife</persName> and <persName id="#sisters">sisters</persName> also were lamenting and weeping, <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> himself displayed a fearless and confident behaviour to all, and cheered them, and he took his supper, as usual, and after resting all night was roused from a deep sleep by Minucius Thermus one of <persName id="#his_colleagues">his colleagues</persName>; and they went down to the Forum with a few persons accompanying them, though many met them and urged them to be on <persName id="#their_guard">their guard</persName>.
When <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> stopped and saw the temple of the <personGrp id="#dioscuri">Dioscuri</personGrp> surrounded by <persName id="#armed_men">armed men</persName> and the steps guarded by <persName id="#gladiators">gladiators</persName>, and <persName id="#metellus">Metellus</persName> himself with <persName id="#caesar">Caesar</persName> sitting above, he turned to <persName id="#his_friends">his friends</persName> and said, "O the daring and cowardly men, to collect such a force of <persName id="#soldiery">soldiery</persName> against <persName id="#a_single_man">a single man</persName> unarmed and defenceless."
Saying this he advanced straight forwards with Thermus; and those who occupied the steps made way for them but they let <persName id="#nobody">nobody</persName> else pass, except that <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> with difficulty pulled <persName id="#munatius">Munatius</persName> by the hand and got him up, and then advancing right onwards, he flung himself between <persName id="#metellus">Metellus</persName> and <persName id="#caesar">Caesar</persName> and there took his seat, and so cut off their communications.
Caesar and Metellus were disconcerted, but the better part of <persName id="#the_people">the people</persName> seeing and admiring the noble bearing and spirit of <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> came nearer, and with shouts encouraged <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> to be of good heart, and they urged one another to stay and keep close together and not to betray their liberty and <persName id="#the_man">the man</persName> who was contending in defence of it.
XXVIII.
<persName id="#the_clerk">The clerk</persName> now produced the law, but <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> would not let him read it, and when <persName id="#metellus">Metellus</persName> took it and began to read, <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> snatched the writing from him; and when <persName id="#metellus">Metellus</persName> who knew the law by heart was beginning to declare it orally, <persName id="#thermus">Thermus</persName> held his mouth with his hand and stopped his voice, till at last <persName id="#metellus">Metellus</persName> seeing that <persName id="#the_men">the men</persName> were making an opposition which he could not resist and that <persName id="#the_people">the people</persName> were beginning to give way to what was best and to change, he ordered <persName id="#armed_men">armed men</persName> to hurry thither from his house with threats and shouts.
This being done, and all having been dispersed except <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName>, who stood there, though he was pelted with stones and pieces of wood from above, <persName id="#murena">Murena</persName>, who had been brought to trial and prosecuted by Cato, did not remain indifferent, but holding his toga in front of him and calling out to those who were throwing missiles, to stop, and finally persuading <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> himself and taking him in his arms, led him off to the temple of the Dioscuri.
Now when Metellus saw that all was clear about the Rostra, and that <persName id="#his_opponents">his opponents</persName> were flying through the Forum, being quite confident that he had got the victory, he ordered <persName id="#the_armed_men">the armed men</persName> to go away, and coming forward in an orderly manner he attempted to conduct the proceedings about the law.
But <persName id="#his_opponents">his opponents</persName> quickly recovering themselves from their rout again advanced with loud and confident shouts, so that <persName id="#the_partizans">the partizans</persName> of Metellus were seized with confusion and fear, for they thought that <persName id="#their_opponents">their opponents</persName> were falling on them with arms which they had provided themselves with from some place or other, and not one of them stood his ground, but all ran away from the Rostra.
When they were thus dispersed, and <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> coming forward partly commended and partly encouraged <persName id="#the_people">the people</persName>, <persName id="#the_people">the people</persName> prepared themselves to put down Metellus by every means, and the Senate assembling declared anew that they would support Cato and resist the law, which they considered to be introducing discord and civil war into <personGrp id="#rome">Rome</personGrp>.
XXIX.
Metellus himsalf was unmoved from his purpose and still bold, but seeing that <persName id="#his_partizans">his partizans</persName> were struck with great terror at Cato, and considered him invincible and that it was impossible to overpower him, he suddenly hurried out to the Forum, and assembling <persName id="#the_people">the people</persName> he said many things calculated to bring odium on Cato, and crying out that he was flying from his tyranny and the conspiracy against <persName id="#pompeius">Pompeius</persName>, for which the city would speedily repent and for their disgracing <persName id="#so_great_a_man">so great a man</persName>, he forthwith set out to <placeName id="#asia">Asia</placeName> to lay all these charges before <persName id="#pompeius">Pompeius</persName>.
Now the fame of <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> was great inasmuch as he had eased the state of the no small burden of the tribuneship, and in a manner had put down the power of Pompeius in <persName id="#the_person">the person</persName> of Metellus; but he got still more credit by not consenting that the Senate, who were minded to do it, should degrade Metellus, and by opposing the measure and praying them not to pass it.
For <persName id="#the_majority">the majority</persName> considered it a token of a humane and moderate temper not to trample on <persName id="#his_enemy">his enemy</persName> nor insult him after he had got the victory; and to the prudent it appeared wise and politic in him not to irritate <persName id="#pompeius">Pompeius</persName>.
After this, Lucullus, who had returned from his campaign, the conclusion and the glory of which Pompeius was considered to have snatched from him, ran the risk of not having a triumph, owing to Caius Memmius stirring up <persName id="#the_people">the people</persName> and bringing charges against him, rather to please <persName id="#pompeius">Pompeius</persName> than out of any private ill-will.
But <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName>, being connected with Lucullus by Lucullus having married <persName id="#cato's_sister_servilia">Cato's sister Servilia</persName>, and also thinking it a scandalous affair, resisted Memmius and exposed himself to much calumny and many imputations.
Finally an attempt being made to eject <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> from his office, on the ground that he was exercising tyrannical power, he so far prevailed as to compel <personGrp id="#memmius">Memmius</personGrp> himself to desist from his prosecution and to give up the contest.
Lucullus accordingly had a triumph, in consideration of which he stuck still more closely to the friendship of Cato, which was to him a protection and bulwark against the power of Pompeius.
<personGrp id="#xxx">XXX</personGrp>.
Pompeius returning from his military command with great reputation, and relying on the splendour and heartiness of his reception for getting everything from <persName id="#the_citizens">the citizens</persName> that he asked for, sent a message to the Senate before his arrival at <personGrp id="#rome">Rome</personGrp>, to ask them to put off the Comitia, that he might be present to assist Piso at his canvass.
<persName id="#the_majority">The majority</persName> were ready to give way, but <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> who did not consider the putting off the Comitia as the chief matter, and wished to cut short the attempts and the hopes of Pompeius, opposed the request and induced the Senate to change their mind and reject it.
This gave Pompeius no little uneasiness, and considering that he should find no slight obstacle in <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName>, if he did not make him his friend, he sent for <persName id="#munatius">Munatius</persName>, an intimate of <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName>, and as Cato had <persName id="#two_marriageable_nieces">two marriageable nieces</persName>, he asked for <persName id="#the_elder">the elder</persName> for <persName id="#his_own_wife">his own wife</persName>, and the younger for <persName id="#his_son">his son</persName>.
Some say that the suit was not for <persName id="#the_nieces">the nieces</persName>, but the daughters of <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName>.
When <persName id="#munatius">Munatius</persName> made the proposal to <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> and <persName id="#his_wife">his wife</persName> and <persName id="#sisters">sisters</persName>, <persName id="#the_women">the women</persName> were delighted above measure at the prospect of the alliance by reason of the greatness and reputation of <persName id="#the_man">the man</persName>; but <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName>, without pause or deliberation, with passion forthwith replied, "Go, <persName id="#munatius">Munatius</persName>, go, and tell <persName id="#pompeius">Pompeius</persName>, that <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> is not to be caught by approaching him through <persName id="#the_women's_chamber">the women's chamber</persName>, but that he is well content to have the friendship of Pompeius, and if <persName id="#pompeius">Pompeius</persName> will act rightly, <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> will show him a friendship more sure than any marriage connection, but he will not give up <persName id="#hostages">hostages</persName> to the reputation of Pompeius contrary to the interests of his country."
<persName id="#the_women">The women</persName> were vexed at these words, and <persName id="#cato's_friends">Cato's friends</persName> blamed his answer as both rude and insolent.
The next thing, however, was that Pompeius while trying to secure the consulship for one of <persName id="#his_friends">his friends</persName>, sent money for <persName id="#the_tribes">the tribes</persName>, and the bribery was notorious, the money being counted out in his gardens.
Accordingly when <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> observed to <persName id="#the_women">the women</persName>, that he who was connected with Pompeius by marriage, must of necessity participate in such measures and be loaded with the disgrace of them, they admitted that he had judged better in rejecting the alliance of Pompeius.
But if we may judge by the result, Cato appears to have made a complete mistake in not accepting the proposed alliance with Pompeius, and allowing him to turn to <persName id="#caesar">Caesar</persName> and to contract a marriage, which, by uniting the power of <persName id="#pompeius">Pompeius</persName> and <persName id="#caesar">Caesar</persName>, nearly overthrew the <personGrp id="#roman">Roman</personGrp> state and did destroy the constitution, nothing of which probably would have happened if <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> had not, through fear of the small errors of Pompeius, overlooked the greatest, which was the allowing him to increase the power of another.
XXXI.
These things, however, were still in the future.
Now when Lucullus was engaged in a contest with <persName id="#pompeius">Pompeius</persName> respecting the arrangements made in <persName id="#pontus">Pontus</persName>, for each of them wished his own arrangements to be confirmed, and <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> gave his aid to Lucullus, who was manifestly wronged, <persName id="#pompeius">Pompeius</persName> being worsted in the Senate and seeking to make himself popular, proposed a division of lands among <persName id="#the_soldiery">the soldiery</persName>.
But when Cato opposed him in this measure also and frustrated the law, <persName id="#pompeius">Pompeius</persName> next attached himself to <persName id="#clodius">Clodius</persName>, the boldest of <persName id="#the_demagogues">the demagogues</persName> at that time, and gained over <persName id="#caesar">Caesar</persName>, to which Cato in a manner gave occasion.
For <persName id="#caesar">Caesar</persName>, who had returned from his praetorship in <personGrp id="#iberia">Iberia</personGrp>, at the same time wished to be <persName id="#a_candidate">a candidate</persName> for the consulship and asked for a triumph.
But as it was the law that those who were <persName id="#candidates">candidates</persName> for a magistracy should be present, and those who were going to have a triumph should stay outside the walls, <persName id="#caesar">Caesar</persName> asked permission of the Senate to solicit the office through means of others.
Many were willing to consent, but <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> spoke against it, and when he saw that the Senators were ready to oblige <persName id="#caesar">Caesar</persName>, he took up the whole day in talking, and thus frustrated the designs, of the Senate.
Caesar accordingly giving up his hopes of a triumph, entered the city, and immediately attached himself to Pompeius, and sought the consulship.
Being elected consul, <persName id="#caesar">Caesar</persName> gave <persName id="#julia">Julia</persName> in marriage to <persName id="#pompeius">Pompeius</persName>, and the two now coalescing against the state, the one introduced laws for giving to the poor allotments and a distribution of land, and the other assisted in supporting these measures.
But Lucullus and <persName id="#cicero">Cicero</persName> siding with <personGrp id="#bibulus">Bibulus</personGrp>, <persName id="#the_other_consul">the other consul</persName>, opposed the measures, and <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> most of all, who already suspected that the friendship and combination of Caesar and <persName id="#pompeius">Pompeius</persName> had no just object, and said that he was not afraid of the distribution of the land, but of the reward for it which those would claim who were gratifying <persName id="#the_multitude">the multitude</persName>, and alluring them by this bait.
XXXII.
By these arguments <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> brought the Senate to an unanimous opinion; and of those without the Senate no small number supported <persName id="#the_senators">the senators</persName>, being annoyed at the unusual measures of Caesar: for what <persName id="#the_boldest_and_most_reckless_tribunes">the boldest and most reckless tribunes</persName> were used to propose for popularity's sake, these very measures Caesar in the possession of consular power adopted, basely and meanly endeavouring to ingratiate himself with <persName id="#the_people">the people</persName>.
<persName id="#caesar's_party">Caesar's party</persName>, therefore, being alarmed, had recourse to violence, and first of all a basket of ordure was thrown upon <personGrp id="#bibulus">Bibulus</personGrp> as he was going down to the Forum, and then <persName id="#the_people">the people</persName> fell on <persName id="#his_lictors">his lictors</persName> and broke the fasces; finally missiles being thrown about, and many being wounded, all the rest ran away from the Forum except <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName>, who walked away slowly, every now and then turning round and cursing <persName id="#the_citizens">the citizens</persName>.
Accordingly <persName id="#caesar's_partisans">Caesar's partisans</persName> not only passed the law for the distribution of land, but they added to it a clause to compel all the Senate to swear that they would maintain the law, and give their aid against any one who should act contrary to it, and they enacted heavy penalties against those who did not swear.
All swore to maintain the law under compulsion, bearing in mind what befell Metellus of old, whom <persName id="#the_people">the people</persName> allowed to be driven from <personGrp id="#italy">Italy</personGrp> because he would not swear to observe a like enactment.
For this reason <persName id="#the_women">the women</persName> of <persName id="#cato's_family">Cato's family</persName> with tears earnestly entreated him to yield and take the oath, and <persName id="#also_his_friends">also his friends</persName> and intimate acquaintance.
But <persName id="#the_person">the person</persName> who most persuaded and induced <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> to take the oath was <persName id="#cicero">Cicero</persName> <persName id="#the_orator">the orator</persName>, who argued and urged that perhaps it was not even right for him to think that he was <persName id="#the_only_man">the only man</persName> who ought to refuse obedience to what had been determined by the common voice; and when it was impossible to undo what had been done, it was altogether senseless and mad to have no regard for himself; and of all evils, he argued, it was the greatest to give up and surrender the state, to the interests of which all his actions were directed, to those who were plotting against it, as if he were glad to be released from all struggles in its behalf; for if <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> did not stand in need of <personGrp id="#rome">Rome</personGrp>, <personGrp id="#rome">Rome</personGrp> stood in need of <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName>, and <persName id="#all_his_friends">all his friends</persName> also did; and among them Cicero said that he was the first, being the object of the designs of <persName id="#clodius">Clodius</persName>, who was clearly proceeding to attack him by means of the tribunitian office.
By these and the like arguments and entreaties, both at home and in the Forum, it is said that <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> was induced to relent, and was prevailed upon with difficulty, and that he came forward to take the oath last of all, except <persName id="#favonius">Favonius</persName>, one of <persName id="#his_friends">his friends</persName> and <persName id="#intimates">intimates</persName>.
XXXIII.
Caesar being encouraged, introduced another law for the division of nearly the whole of <personGrp id="#campania">Campania</personGrp> among the poor and needy.
<persName id="#nobody">Nobody</persName> spoke against it except <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName>; and him <persName id="#caesar">Caesar</persName> caused to be dragged from the <personGrp id="#rostra">Rostra</personGrp> to prison, <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> the while remitting nothing of his freedom of speech, but as he went along, at the same time speaking about the law and advising them to cease attempting such political measures.
The Senate followed with downcast countenances, and the best part of <persName id="#the_people">the people</persName>, much annoyed and troubled, though they said nothing, so that Caesar did not fail to see that they were displeased; but out of self-will and expectation that Cato would appeal and have recourse to entreaties, he continued leading him to prison.
But when it was plain that <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> intended to do nothing at all, <persName id="#caesar">Caesar</persName>, overcome by shame and the ill opinion of the thing, privately persuaded one of <persName id="#the_tribunes">the tribunes</persName> to rescue Cato.
By these laws, however, and these grants of land, they so cajoled <persName id="#the_people">the people</persName>, that they voted to Caesar the government of <persName id="#illyricum">Illyricum</persName> and all <personGrp id="#gaul">Gaul</personGrp> with <persName id="#four_legions">four legions</persName> for five years, though Cato warned them that they would by their own votes plant <persName id="#the_tyrant">the tyrant</persName> in the Acropolis; and they transferred by illegal means <persName id="#publius_clodius">Publius Clodius</persName> from the patrician order to <persName id="#the_plebeians">the plebeians</persName>, and made <persName id="#the_man">the man</persName> a tribune, who was willing to do anything in his public capacity to serve them, on condition that they would let <persName id="#cicero">Cicero</persName> be driven out; and they made <persName id="#consuls_piso_calpurnius">consuls Piso Calpurnius</persName>, <persName id="#the_father">the father</persName> of <persName id="#caesar's_wife">Caesar's wife</persName>, and <persName id="#gabinius_aulus">Gabinius Aulus</persName>, <persName id="#a_man">a man</persName> from the lap of <persName id="#pompeius">Pompeius</persName>, as those say who were acquainted with his habits and life.
XXXIV.
But though <persName id="#caesar">Caesar</persName> and <persName id="#his_party">his party</persName> had thus violently got possession of the power, and had one part of <persName id="#the_citizens">the citizens</persName> at their command through their grants, and another part through fear, they still dreaded <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName>.
For even when they did get the advantage over him, the fact that it was with difficulty and labour, and not without shame and exposure that they hardly forced their purpose, was annoying and vexatious.
Clodius, indeed, did not expect to be able to put down Cicero so long as <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> was at home, and as he was contriving how to effect this, he sent for <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> as soon as he was in his office, and addressed him to the effect that he considered <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> to be <persName id="#the_purest_man">the purest man</persName> of all the <personGrp id="#romans">Romans</personGrp>, and he was ready to prove the sincerity of his opinion by his acts, and he said that though many persons were soliciting the commission to <personGrp id="#cyprus">Cyprus</personGrp> and Ptolemaeus, and asking to be sent, he thought <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> alone worthy of it, and that he gladly offered him the favour.
On <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> crying out that the thing was a snare and insult and not a favour, <persName id="#clodius">Clodius</persName> replied in an insolent and contemptuous manner, "Well, if you don't like it, you shall make the voyage against your liking;" and immediately going before <persName id="#the_people">the people</persName> he got the mission of <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> confirmed by a law.
When <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> was leaving <personGrp id="#rome">Rome</personGrp>, <persName id="#clodius">Clodius</persName> allowed him neither ship nor soldier nor attendant except <persName id="#two_clerks">two clerks</persName>, one of whom was <persName id="#a_thief">a thief</persName> and <persName id="#a_thorough_knave">a thorough knave</persName>, and the other was <persName id="#a_client">a client</persName> of Clodius.
And as if he had given him but small occupations with the affairs of <personGrp id="#cyprus">Cyprus</personGrp> and Ptolemaeus, <persName id="#clodius">Clodius</persName> commissioned him also to restore <persName id="#the_byzantine_fugitives">the Byzantine fugitives</persName>, his wish being that <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> should be as long as possible from <personGrp id="#rome">Rome</personGrp> during his tribuneship.
XXXV.
Being under such compulsion, <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> advised Cicero, who was pressed by <persName id="#his_enemies">his enemies</persName>, not to raise any commotion nor to involve the city in a contest and bloodshed, but by yielding to the times to be again <persName id="#the_saviour">the saviour</persName> of his country; and sending forward to Cyprus Canidius, to yield without a struggle, assuring him that he should want neither money nor respect, for that <persName id="#the_people">the people</persName> would give him the priesthood of <persName id="#the_goddess">the goddess</persName> at <personGrp id="#paphos">Paphos</personGrp>.
Cato himself stayed in <persName id="#rhodes">Rhodes</persName> making preparation and waiting for the answers.
In the meantime <personGrp id="#ptolemaeus">Ptolemaeus</personGrp>, <personGrp id="#king_of_egypt">King of Egypt</personGrp>, left <personGrp id="#alexandria">Alexandria</personGrp> in anger after quarrelling with <persName id="#the_citizens">the citizens</persName>, and set sail for <personGrp id="#rome">Rome</personGrp> in the hope that Caesar and <persName id="#pompeius">Pompeius</persName> would restore him with a military force; and as he wished to see <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> he sent a message, expecting that <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> would come to him.
Cato happened to be then undergoing a purging, and he answered that Ptolemaeus must come, if he wished to see him; and when <persName id="#the_king">the king</persName> did come, <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> neither advanced to meet him nor rose, but saluted him as one of <persName id="#his_ordinary_visitors">his ordinary visitors</persName> and bade him be seated; and by this behaviour <persName id="#the_king">the king</persName> was at first disturbed, and was amazed at the contrast between <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName>'s haughty behaviour and rough manners, and the meanness and simplicity of <persName id="#the_man's_attire">the man's attire</persName>.
But when he had begun to talk with him about his own affairs, and listened to words full of wisdom and plain-speaking, for <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> reproved him and showed what a happy condition he had left and to what servitude and toils and corruption and love of aggrandisement in <persName id="#the_chief_men">the chief men</persName> of the <personGrp id="#romans">Romans</personGrp> he was subjecting himself, whom scarcely <personGrp id="#egypt">Egypt</personGrp> would satisfy if it were all turned into silver, and <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> advised <persName id="#the_king">the king</persName> to return and be reconciled to <persName id="#his_people">his people</persName>, and said that he was ready to sail with him and assist in bringing about an accommodation, <persName id="#the_king">the king</persName>, as if he had been brought to his senses from some madness or delirium by the words of Cato, and perceiving the integrity and judgment of <persName id="#the_man">the man</persName>, was resolved to follow his advice.
However, <persName id="#the_king">the king</persName> was again turned by <persName id="#his_friends">his friends</persName> to his original design, but as soon as he was in <personGrp id="#rome">Rome</personGrp> and was approaching the door of one of <persName id="#the_magistrates">the magistrates</persName>, he groaned over his ill resolve, as if he had rejected, not the advice of <persName id="#a_good_man">a good man</persName>, but the prophetic warning of <persName id="#a_deity">a deity</persName>.
XXXVI.
The Ptolemaeus in <personGrp id="#cyprus">Cyprus</personGrp>, to Cato's good luck, poisoned himself; and as it was said that he had left a large sum of money, <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> determined to go to <persName id="#byzantium">Byzantium</persName> himself, and he sent <persName id="#his_nephew">his nephew</persName> <persName id="#brutus">Brutus</persName> to <personGrp id="#cyprus">Cyprus</personGrp>, because he did not altogether trust Canidius.
After bringing <persName id="#the_exiles">the exiles</persName> to terms with <persName id="#their_fellow-citizens">their fellow-citizens</persName> and leaving <persName id="#byzantium">Byzantium</persName> at peace with itself, he sailed to <personGrp id="#cyprus">Cyprus</personGrp>.
Now as there was a great quantity of movables, such as suited <persName id="#a_royal_household">a royal household</persName>, consisting of cups, tables, precious stones and purple, all which was to be sold and turned into money, <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> being desirous to do everything with the greatest exactness and to bring up everything to the highest price, and to be present everywhere and to apply the strictest reckoning, would not trust even to the usages of the market, but suspecting all alike, <persName id="#assistants">assistants</persName>, <persName id="#criers">criers</persName>, <persName id="#purchasers">purchasers</persName> and <persName id="#friends">friends</persName>, in fine, by talking to <persName id="#the_purchasers">the purchasers</persName> singly and urging them to bid, he in this way got most of the things sold that were put up for sale.
<persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> thus offended the rest of <persName id="#his_friends">his friends</persName> by showing that he did not trust them, and <persName id="#munatius">Munatius</persName>, the most intimate of all, he put into a state of resentment that was well nigh past cure; so that when <persName id="#caesar">Caesar</persName> was writing his book against <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName>, this passage in the charges against him furnished matter for the most bitter invective.
XXXVII.
<persName id="#munatius">Munatius</persName>, however, states that his anger against <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> arose not by reason of Cato's distrust of him, but his contemptuous behaviour, and a certain jealousy of his own in regard to Canidius; for <persName id="#munatius">Munatius</persName> also published a book about <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName>, which <persName id="#thrasea">Thrasea</persName> chiefly followed.
He says that he arrived after the rest in <personGrp id="#cyprus">Cyprus</personGrp> and found very poor accommodation prepared for him; and that on going to <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName>'s door he was repulsed, because <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> was engaged about some matters in the house with Canidius, and when he complained of this in reasonable terms, he got an answer which was not reasonable and to the effect: That excessive affection, as Theophrastus says, is in danger of often becoming the cause of hatred, "for," continued <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName>, "you, by reason of your very great affection for me, are vexed when you suppose that you receive less respect than is your due.
But I employ Canidius because I have made trial of him and trust him more than others, for he came at the first and has shown himself to be <persName id="#an_honest_man">an honest man</persName>."
This, says <persName id="#munatius">Munatius</persName>, <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> said to him, when they two were alone, but that <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> afterwards told it to Canidius; and accordingly when <persName id="#munatius">Munatius</persName> heard of it, as he says, he did not go to <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName>'s table nor to his counsels when he was invited; and when <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> threatened that he would take pledges from him, which the <personGrp id="#romans">Romans</personGrp> do in the case of those who refuse to obey a command, that without caring for <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName>'s threats he sailed away from <personGrp id="#cyprus">Cyprus</personGrp> and for a long time continued to be angry with him.
That afterwards <persName id="#marcia">Marcia</persName>, for she was still <persName id="#the_wife">the wife</persName> of <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName>, having spoken with <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName>, both <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> and he happened to be invited to supper by <placeName id="#barcas">Barcas</placeName>; and <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName>, who came in after <persName id="#the_guests">the guests</persName> were seated, asked where he should recline.
<persName id="#upon_barcas">Upon Barcas</persName> answering, "Where he pleased," <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> looking about him said he would take his place near <persName id="#munatius">Munatius</persName>; and going round he did take his place near him, but showed him no other sign of friendly feeling during the supper.
However, upon <persName id="#marcia">Marcia</persName> preferring a second request, <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> wrote to him to say that he wished to see him on some matter, and that he went early in the morning to the house and was detained by <persName id="#marcia">Marcia</persName> till all the rest went way, when <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> came in and throwing both his arms round him saluted and received him with all signs of friendship.
Now I have told this at some length, because I consider such things to contain a certain evidence for the exhibition and perception of character no less than public and great acts.
XXXVIII.
Cato got together nearly seven thousand talents of silver, and being afraid of the length of the voyage, he had many vessels made, each of which contained two talents and five hundred drachmae, and he fastened to each vessel a long rope, to the end of which was attached a very large piece of cork, with the view, that if the ship were wrecked, the cork holding the vessels suspended in the deep sea might indicate the place.
Now the money, with the exception of a small part, was safely conveyed; but though he had accounts of all his administration carefully drawn up in two books, he saved neither of them.
One of them was in the care of <persName id="#his_freedman_philargyros">his freedman Philargyros</persName>, who set sail from <personGrp id="#kenchreae">Kenchreae</personGrp>, but was wrecked, and lost the book and all the cargo with it: the other he had safely carried as far as Corcyra, where he pitched his tent in the Agora; but <persName id="#the_sailors">the sailors</persName> on account of the cold having lighted many fires, the tents were burnt in the night, and the book was destroyed.
<persName id="#the_king's_managers">The king's managers</persName> who were present were ready to stop the mouths of <persName id="#the_enemies">the enemies</persName> and <persName id="#detractors">detractors</persName> of <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName>; but the matter gave him annoyance for other reasons.
For it was not to prove his own integrity, but to set an example of exact dealing to others that he was ambitious to produce his accounts, and this was the cause of his vexation.
XXXIX.
Cato's arrival with the ships did not pass unobserved by the <personGrp id="#romans">Romans</personGrp>, for <persName id="#all_the_magistrates">all the magistrates</persName> and <persName id="#priests">priests</persName>, and all the Senate and a great part of <persName id="#the_people">the people</persName> met him at the river, so that both the banks were covered, and Cato's voyage upwards was not inferior to a triumph in show and splendour.
Yet it seemed to some to be a perverse and stubborn thing, that though <persName id="#the_consuls">the consuls</persName> and <persName id="#praetors">praetors</persName> were present, <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> neither landed to meet them nor stopped his course, but sweeping along the shore in a royal galley of six banks, he never stopped till he had moored his ships in the dockyard.
However, when the money was carried along through the Forum, <persName id="#the_people">the people</persName> were amazed at the quantity, and the Senate assembling voted together with suitable thanks that an extraordinary praetorship should be given to Cato, and that he should wear a dress with a purple border when he was present at the public spectacles.
<persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> protested against both these distinctions, but he recommended the Senate to emancipate <persName id="#nikias">Nikias</persName>, <persName id="#the_king's_steward">the king's steward</persName>, to whose care and integrity he bore testimony.
At that time <persName id="#philippus">Philippus</persName>, <persName id="#the_father">the father</persName> of <persName id="#marcia">Marcia</persName>, was <persName id="#consul">consul</persName>, and in a manner the dignity and power of the office were transferred to <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName>, for <persName id="#the_colleague">the colleague</persName> of Philippus paid no less respect to <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> on account of his merit than on account of his relationship to Philippus.
XL.
When <persName id="#cicero">Cicero</persName> had returned from the exile into which he was driven by <persName id="#clodius">Clodius</persName>, and was now <persName id="#a_powerful_man">a powerful man</persName>, he forcibly pulled down and destroyed in the absence of <persName id="#clodius">Clodius</persName>, the tribunitian tablets which <persName id="#clodius">Clodius</persName> had recorded and placed in the Capitol; and the Senate having been assembled about this business, and <persName id="#clodius">Clodius</persName> making it a matter of accusation, Cicero said that inasmuch as <persName id="#clodius">Clodius</persName> had been made tribune in an illegal manner, all that had been done during his tribunate and recorded ought to be ineffectual and invalid.
But <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> took exception to what Cicero said, and at length he rose and declared, that he was of opinion that there was nothing sound or good in any degree in the administration of <persName id="#clodius">Clodius</persName>, but that if <persName id="#any_man">any man</persName> was for rescinding all that <persName id="#clodius">Clodius</persName> had done in his tribunate, all his own measures relating to <personGrp id="#cyprus">Cyprus</personGrp> were thereby rescinded, and his mission had not been legal, having been proposed by <persName id="#a_man">a man</persName> who was not legally <persName id="#tribune">tribune</persName>: he maintained that <persName id="#clodius">Clodius</persName> had not been illegally elected tribune by virtue of being adopted out of the patrician body into <persName id="#a_plebeian_family">a plebeian family</persName>, for the law allowed this; but if he had been <persName id="#a_bad_magistrate">a bad magistrate</persName>, like others, it was fitting to call to account <persName id="#the_man">the man</persName> who had done wrong, and not to annul the office which had been wronged also.
In consequence of this, <persName id="#cicero">Cicero</persName> was angry with <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName>, and for a long time ceased all friendly intercourse with him: however, they were afterwards reconciled.
XLI.
After this <persName id="#pompeius">Pompeius</persName> and Crassus had a meeting with Caesar, who had come across the <placeName id="#alps">Alps</placeName>, in which they agreed that they should seek a second consulship; and when they were established in it, they should cause another period in <persName id="#caesar">Caesar</persName>'s government as long as the first to be given him by the vote of <persName id="#the_people">the people</persName>, and to themselves the chief of the provinces and money and military forces: the which was a conspiracy for the division of the supreme power and the destruction of the constitution.
Now though <persName id="#many_honest_men">many honest men</persName> were at this time preparing to be <persName id="#candidates">candidates</persName> for the consulship, they were deterred by seeing Pompeius and <persName id="#crassus">Crassus</persName> canvassing; but <persName id="#lucius_domitius">Lucius Domitius</persName> alone, <persName id="#the_husband">the husband</persName> of <personGrp id="#porcia">Porcia</personGrp>, <persName id="#the_sister">the sister</persName> of <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName>, was induced by Cato not to give way or to yield, as the contest was not for office but for the liberty of <personGrp id="#rome">Rome</personGrp>.
And indeed it was currently said among that part of <persName id="#the_citizens">the citizens</persName> who were still of sober thoughts, that they ought not to allow the consular office to become completely overbearing and oppressive by permitting the power of <personGrp id="#crassus">Crassus</personGrp> and <persName id="#pompeius">Pompeius</persName> to be combined, but that they should deprive one of them of the office.
And they ranged themselves on the side of <persName id="#domitius">Domitius</persName>, urging and encouraging him to keep to his purpose; for many, they argued, even of those who said nothing by reason of fear, would help him with their votes.
<persName id="#the_party">The party</persName> of Pompeius and <persName id="#crassus">Crassus</persName> fearing this, laid an ambuscade for <persName id="#domitius">Domitius</persName> as he was going down to the Campus <persName id="#martius">Martius</persName> early in the morning, by torch-light.
First of <persName id="#all_the_man">all the man</persName> who was lighting <persName id="#domitius">Domitius</persName> and standing close by him was struck and fell down dead; and after him others also being wounded, there was a general flight of all except <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> and <persName id="#domitius">Domitius</persName>; for <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> held <persName id="#domitius">Domitius</persName> though he himself was wounded in the arm, and urged him to stay and so long as there was breath in them, not to give up the struggle for liberty against <persName id="#the_tyrants">the tyrants</persName> who showed how they would use their power, by making their way to it through such acts of wrong.
XLII.
<persName id="#domitius">Domitius</persName>, however, did not face the danger, but fled to his house, upon which Pompeius and <persName id="#crassus">Crassus</persName>, were elected.
Yet <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> did not give up the contest, but came forward as <persName id="#a_candidate">a candidate</persName> for a praetorship, because he wished to have a strong position in his struggles with them and not to be himself <persName id="#a_private_man">a private man</persName> while he was opposing those who were in office.
Pompeius and Crassus being afraid of this, and considering that the praetorship by reason of Cato would become a match for the consulship, in the first place on a sudden and without the knowledge of many of the body, summoned the Senate, and got a vote passed that those who were elected praetors should enter on office forthwith and should not let the time fixed by law intervene, during which time prosecutions were allowed of those who had bribed <persName id="#the_people">the people</persName>.
In the next place, now that they had by the vote of the Senate made bribery free from all responsibility, they brought forward their own tools and <persName id="#friends">friends</persName> as <persName id="#candidates">candidates</persName> for the praetorship, themselves giving the bribe-money, and themselves standing by while the voting was going on.
But when the merit and good name of Cato were getting the superiority even over all this, the many for very shame considering it a great crime by their votes to sell <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName>, whom it were even honourable to purchase for the state as <persName id="#praetor">praetor</persName>, and <persName id="#the_tribe">the tribe</persName> which was first called voted for him, <persName id="#pompeius">Pompeius</persName> all at once, falsely saying he had heard thunder, dissolved <persName id="#the_assembly">the assembly</persName>, for it was the custom of the <personGrp id="#romans">Romans</personGrp> to view such tokens as inauspicious, and not to ratify anything when there had been signs from heaven.
Thereafter, by employing excessive bribery and driving <persName id="#all_the_honest_folks">all the honest folks</persName> from the Campus they brought about by violence that <placeName id="#vatinius">Vatinius</placeName> should be elected praetor instead of <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName>.
Upon this it is said that those who had given their votes thus illegally and dishonestly, forthwith skulked away; and a certain tribune forming on the spot a meeting of those who were assembling together and expressing their dissatisfaction, <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> came before them, and as if inspired by <persName id="#the_gods">the gods</persName>, foretold everything that would happen to the state, and urged <persName id="#the_citizens">the citizens</persName> to oppose Pompeius and <persName id="#crassus">Crassus</persName> as being privy to such measures and engaging in a course of policy, on account of which they feared Cato lest, if he were <persName id="#praetor">praetor</persName>, he should get the advantage over them.
And finally as he went home, he was attended by such a crowd as <persName id="#not_even_all_the_praetors">not even all the praetors</persName> together, who were elected, had to accompany them.
XLIII.
When <persName id="#caius_trebonius">Caius Trebonius</persName> drew up a law for the division of the provinces between <persName id="#the_consuls">the consuls</persName>, to the effect that one of them should have the government of <personGrp id="#iberia">Iberia</personGrp> and <personGrp id="#libya">Libya</personGrp>, and the other <personGrp id="#syria">Syria</personGrp> and <personGrp id="#egypt">Egypt</personGrp>, to attack and carry on war against whom they pleased with naval and military forces, the rest despairing of all opposition and hindrance even desisted from speaking against the measure, and when <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> got up on the Rostra before the question was put to the vote, and expressed a wish to speak, he with difficulty obtained leave to speak for two hours.
After <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> had occupied this time with much speaking, and alleging of arguments and prophetic warnings, they would not let him speak longer, but <persName id="#an_officer">an officer</persName> went up and pulled him down while he was still keeping his place on the Rostra.
But inasmuch as he continued to cry out from the place where he was standing below, and had persons to listen to him and join in his dissatisfaction, <persName id="#the_officer">the officer</persName> again laid hold of him and taking him away, put him out of the Forum.
But scarcely was he let loose when he returned and made his way to the Rostra with loud shouts, urging <persName id="#the_citizens">the citizens</persName> to aid him.
This being repeated several times, Trebonius in a passion ordered him to be led to prison, and the crowd followed listening to him talking as he went along, so that Trebonius was afraid and let him go.
In this manner <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> took up all that day: but on the following days by terrifying some of <persName id="#the_citizens">the citizens</persName> and gaining over others by favours and by bribes, and with <persName id="#armed_men">armed men</persName> preventing Aquilius one of <persName id="#the_tribunes">the tribunes</persName> from coming out of the senate house, and by ejecting from the Forum <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> himself, who called out that there had been thunder, and by wounding no small number, and even killing some, they forcibly carried the law, in consequence of which many persons in passion crowded together and pelted the statues of Pompeius.
Cato, however, who came up to them stopped this; and further, when a law was proposed respecting the provinces and <persName id="#armies">armies</persName> of Caesar, <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> no longer addressed himself to <persName id="#the_people">the people</persName>, but turning to <persName id="#pompeius">Pompeius</persName> himself he adjured and forewarned him, that he did not see that he was now taking up <persName id="#caesar">Caesar</persName> on his shoulders, but that when he began to feel the weight of his burden and to be mastered by it, having neither power to rid himself of it nor strength to bear it, he would fall with it upon the state, and then he would remember <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName>'s advice and see that it concerned no less the interests of Pompeius than honour and justice.
Though <persName id="#pompeius">Pompeius</persName> heard this often, he cared not for it and let it pass, not believing there would be any change in <persName id="#caesar">Caesar</persName>, because he trusted in his own good fortune and power.
XLIV.
For the following year <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> was chosen praetor, but he was considered not to add so much dignity and honour to the office by his good administration, as to detract from it and bring it into disrepute by often going to the Rostra without his shoes and his tunic, and in this attire presiding at trials of <persName id="#men">men</persName> of rank in matters of life and death.
Some also say that even after dinner, when he had drunk wine, he would transact business; but this at least is untruly said.
<persName id="#the_people">The people</persName> being now corrupted by the bribery of those who were ambitious of office, and <persName id="#the_majority">the majority</persName> being accustomed to receive money for their votes as if in the way of a regular trade, <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> wishing to eradicate completely this disease in the state, persuaded the Senate to make a decree, that if those who were elected magistrates should have none ready to accuse them, they should themselves be compelled to come forward before <persName id="#a_sworn_court">a sworn court</persName> and give an account of their election.
<persName id="#the_candidates">The candidates</persName> for magistracies were vexed at this, and still more vexed were the mass who received the bribe-money.
Accordingly in the morning when <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> had gone to the tribunal, <persName id="#the_people">the people</persName> in a body pressing upon him, cried out, abused him, and pelted him so that <persName id="#every_person">every person</persName> fled from the tribunal, and <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> himself being shoved from his place by the crowd and carried along with it, with difficulty laid hold of the Rostra.
Thereupon getting up, by the boldness and firmness of his demeanour, <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> forthwith mastered the tumult, and stopped the shouting, and after saying what was suitable to the occasion and being listened to with perfect quiet, he put an end to the disturbance.
When the Senate were bestowing praise upon him, he said, "But I cannot praise you, who left <persName id="#a_praetor">a praetor</persName> in danger and did not come to his help."
But of <persName id="#the_candidates">the candidates</persName> for magistracies <persName id="#every_man">every man</persName> felt himself in a difficult position, being afraid to give bribes himself, and being afraid that he should lose the office if another did it.
Accordingly it was agreed among them that they should come together to one place, and each lay down one hundred and twenty-five thousand drachmae of silver, and all should then seek the office in a right and just way, and that he who broke the terms and employed bribery, should lose his money.
Having agreed to these terms they chose Cato as depositary and umpire and witness, and bringing the money, they offered to place it with him; and they had the terms of the agreement drawn up before him, but <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> took sureties instead of the money, and would not receive the money itself.
When the day for the election came, <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> taking his place by <persName id="#the_presiding_tribune">the presiding tribune</persName> and watching the vote, discovered that one of those who had entered into the engagement, was playing foul, and he ordered him to pay the money to the rest.
But they, commending his uprightness and admiring it, waived the penalty, considering that they had sufficient satisfaction from <persName id="#the_wrong-doer">the wrong-doer</persName>; but <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> offended all the rest and got very great odium from this, it being as if he assumed to himself the power of the Senate and of the courts of justice and of <persName id="#the_magistrates">the magistrates</persName>.
For the opinion and the credit of no one virtue makes <persName id="#people">people</persName> more envious than that of justice, because both aepower and credit among the many follow it chiefly.
For <persName id="#people">people</persName> do not merely honour the just, as they do the brave, nor do they admire them, as they do the wise, but they even love the just, and have confidence in them and give them credit.
But as to the brave and wise, they fear the one, and give no credit to the other; and besides this, they think that the brave and the wise excel by nature rather than by their own will; and with respect to courage and wisdom, they consider the one to be a certain sharpness, and the other a firmness of soul; but inasmuch as <persName id="#any_man">any man</persName> who chooses, has it in his power to be just, they have most abhorrence of injustice as badness that is without excuse.
XLV.
Wherefore all the great were <persName id="#enemies">enemies</persName> of Cato, as being reproved by his conduct: and as Pompeius viewed <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName>'s reputation even as a nullification of his own power, he was continually setting persons on to abuse him, among whom <persName id="#clodius">Clodius</persName> also was one, <persName id="#the_demagogue">the demagogue</persName>, who had again insensibly attached himself to <persName id="#pompeius">Pompeius</persName>, and was crying out against <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> on the ground that he had appropriated to his own purposes much money in <personGrp id="#cyprus">Cyprus</personGrp>, and was hostile to Pompeius because Pompeius had rejected a marriage with <persName id="#cato's_daughter">Cato's daughter</persName>.
<persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> replied that he had brought to the city from <personGrp id="#cyprus">Cyprus</personGrp>, without the aid of a single horse or <persName id="#soldier">soldier</persName>, more money than <persName id="#pompeius">Pompeius</persName> had brought back from so many wars and triumphs after disturbing the habitable world, and that he never chose <persName id="#pompeius">Pompeius</persName> to make a marriage alliance with, not because he considered <persName id="#pompeius">Pompeius</persName> unworthy, but because he saw the difference between his polity and that of <persName id="#pompeius">Pompeius</persName>.
"For my part," continued <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName>, "I declined a province when it was offered to me after my praetorship, but Pompeius has got some provinces, and he also offers some to others; and now, last of all, he has lent to <persName id="#caesar">Caesar</persName> a force of <persName id="#six_thousand_legionary_soldiers">six thousand legionary soldiers</persName> for <personGrp id="#gaul">Gaul</personGrp>, which neither did <persName id="#caesar">Caesar</persName> ask of you, nor did <persName id="#pompeius">Pompeius</persName> give with your assent; but forces to such an amount and arms and horses are gifts from private persons and things of mutual exchange.
And being called Imperator and governor he has given up to others <persName id="#the_armies">the armies</persName> and the provinces, and he himself sits down close to the city raising commotions at the elections and contriving disturbances, from which it is manifest that he is intriguing to get by means of anarchy a monarchy for himself."
XLVI.
In this fashion <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> defended himself against Pompeius.
But <persName id="#marcus_favonius">Marcus Favonius</persName>, <persName id="#an_intimate_friend">an intimate friend</persName> and <persName id="#admirer">admirer</persName> of <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName>, just as Apollodorus of Phalerum is said to have been of Socrates of old, being <persName id="#a_passionate_man">a passionate man</persName> and one who was violently moved by his principles, did not with any temper or moderation, but intemperately attack <persName id="#pompeius">Pompeius</persName>, like <persName id="#a_man">a man</persName> under the influence of drink and somewhat mad.
<persName id="#favonius">Favonius</persName> was <persName id="#a_candidate">a candidate</persName> for the aedileship and was losing his election, when <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName>, who was present, observed that the voting tablets were written in one hand, and so proved the knavery, and by appealing to <persName id="#the_tribunes">the tribunes</persName> stopped the return.
Afterwards when <persName id="#favonius">Favonius</persName> was made aedile, <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> both administered the other duties of the aedileship, and superintended the exhibitions in the theatre, giving to <persName id="#the_actors">the actors</persName> not crowns of gold, but as is the fashion of <personGrp id="#olympia">Olympia</personGrp>, crowns of wild olive, and instead of costly presents, giving to the <personGrp id="#greeks">Greeks</personGrp>, turnips and lettuces and radishes and parsley; and to the <personGrp id="#romans">Romans</personGrp>, earthen jars of wine, and hogs' flesh, and figs and gourds, and bundles of wood, at the thrift of which gifts some laughed, but others treated the matter in a respectful way, seeing the austere and serious countenance of <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> imperceptibly assuming a pleasant expression.
Finally, <persName id="#favonius">Favonius</persName>, mingling with, the crowd and sitting among <persName id="#the_spectators">the spectators</persName>, applauded <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName>, and called out to him to give to those who were distinguishing themselves, and to honour them, and he urged <persName id="#the_spectators">the spectators</persName> to the same effect, inasmuch as he had surrendered all his authority to Cato.
Now in the other theatre, <persName id="#curio">Curio</persName>, <persName id="#the_colleague">the colleague</persName> of <persName id="#favonius">Favonius</persName>, was conducting the celebration in splendid style, but still <persName id="#the_people">the people</persName> left him to go to the other place, and they readily joined in the amusement of <personGrp id="#favonius">Favonius</personGrp> playing a private part and <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> the part of <persName id="#the_superintendent">the superintendent</persName> of the exhibitions.
And <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> did this to disparage the thing and to show that when <persName id="#a_man">a man</persName> is in sport he should use sportive ways, and accompany it with unpretending kindness rather than with much preparation and great cost, bestowing great care and trouble on things of no value.
XLVII.
Now when <persName id="#scipio">Scipio</persName> and <persName id="#hypsaeus">Hypsaeus</persName> and <persName id="#milo">Milo</persName> were <persName id="#candidates">candidates</persName> for the consulship, and were employing not merely those wrongful ways that were now familiar and had become usual in matters political, the giving of gifts and bribery, but were plainly pushing on through arms and slaughter to civil war, in their daring and madness, and some persons were urging <persName id="#pompeius">Pompeius</persName> to preside over the comitia, <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> at first opposed this and said, that the laws should not owe their maintenance to Pompeius, but that <persName id="#pompeius">Pompeius</persName> should owe his security to the laws.
However, when there had been an anarchy for some time, and <persName id="#three_armies">three armies</persName> were occupying the Forum daily, and the mischief had well nigh become past checking, he determined in favour of putting affairs in the hands of <persName id="#pompeius">Pompeius</persName> before the extreme necessity arrived, by the voluntary favour of the Senate, and by employing the most moderate of unconstitutional means as a healing measure for the settlement of what was most important, to bring on the monarchy rather than to let the civil dissensions result in a monarchy.
Accordingly Bibulus, who was <persName id="#a_friend">a friend</persName> of Cato, proposed that they ought to elect <persName id="#pompeius_sole_consul">Pompeius sole consul</persName>, for that either matters would be put into a good condition by his settlement of them, or that the state would be enslaved by <persName id="#the_best_man">the best man</persName> in it.
Cato rose and spoke in favour of the proposal, which <persName id="#nobody">nobody</persName> could have expected, and recommended any government as better than no government; and he added, that he expected that Pompeius would manage present affairs best, and would protect the state with which he was intrusted.
XLVIII.
Pompeius being thus declared <persName id="#consul">consul</persName> prayed <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> to come to him to the suburbs: and on his arrival <persName id="#pompeius">Pompeius</persName> received him in a friendly manner with salutations and pressing of hands, and after acknowledging his obligations he entreated <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> to be <persName id="#his_adviser">his adviser</persName> and <persName id="#his_assessor">his assessor</persName> in the consulship.
But <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> replied, that neither had he said what he first said out of evil disposition towards Pompeius, nor had he said what he last said in order to win his favour, but everything for the interest of the state; accordingly he observed that he would give Pompeius his advice when he was privately invited, but that in <persName id="#public">public</persName>, even if he should not be invited, he would certainly say what he thought.
And he did as he said.
In the first place, when <persName id="#pompeius">Pompeius</persName> was proposing laws with new penalties and severe proceedings against those who had already bribed <persName id="#the_people">the people</persName>, <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> advised him not to care about the past, but to attend to the future, for he said, it was not easy to determine at what point the inquiry into past offences should stop, and if penalties be imposed after the offences, those would be hardly dealt with who were punished by a law which they were not breaking at the time of their wrong-doing.
In the next place, when <persName id="#many_men">many men</persName> of rank were under trial, some of whom were <persName id="#friends">friends</persName> and relations of Pompeius, <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> observing that <persName id="#pompeius">Pompeius</persName> was giving way to the greater part of them and yielding, rebuked him firmly and roused him up.
Though <persName id="#pompeius">Pompeius</persName> himself had caused a law to be passed which did not allow the panegyrics which used to be pronounced on those who were under trial, he wrote a panegyric on <persName id="#munatius_plancus">Munatius Plancus</persName> on the occasion of his trial and handed it in, but <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> by stopping his ears with his hands, for he happened to be one of <persName id="#the_judices">the judices</persName>, prevented the testimonial from being read.
<persName id="#plancus">Plancus</persName> challenged <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> as one of <persName id="#the_judices">the judices</persName> after the speeches, but nevertheless he was convicted.
And altogether <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> was a kind of thing difficult and unmanageable for persons accused, as they were neither willing to have him to be a judex, nor could they venture to challenge him.
For not a few were convicted because, by being unwilling to have <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> for one of <persName id="#their_judices">their judices</persName>, they were considered to show that they had no confidence in the justice of their cause; and <persName id="#their_revilers">their revilers</persName> even charged it upon some as matter of great reproach that they would not have <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> as one of <persName id="#their_judices">their judices</persName> when he was proposed.
XLIX.
Now when <persName id="#caesar">Caesar</persName>, though he kept close to <persName id="#his_armies">his armies</persName> in <personGrp id="#gaul">Gaul</personGrp> and stuck to arms, was still employing gifts and money and <persName id="#friends">friends</persName> to secure his power in the city, <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName>'s admonitions roused Pompeius from his former long continued state of incredulity, and he began to be afraid of the danger; but as he was somewhat hesitating and spiritlessly procrastinating all attempts at prevention, Cato resolved to be <persName id="#a_candidate">a candidate</persName> for the consulship with the view of either forthwith wresting <persName id="#caesar">Caesar</persName>'s arms from him or demonstrating his designs.
But <persName id="#the_rival_candidates">the rival candidates</persName> were both <persName id="#popular_men">popular men</persName>: and <persName id="#sulpicius">Sulpicius</persName> had already derived much advantage from <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName>'s reputation in the state and his influence.
He therefore seemed to be doing what was neither just nor grateful, but yet Cato found no fault with him.
"What is it strange," said he, "if <persName id="#a_man">a man</persName> does not give up to another the thing which he thinks to be the greatest of goods?" But Cato by persuading the Senate to pass a Consultum that those who were <persName id="#candidates">candidates</persName> for the office should canvass <persName id="#the_people">the people</persName> themselves, and should not solicit through <persName id="#any_other_person">any other person</persName>, not even by <persName id="#such_person">such person</persName> going about to see <persName id="#the_citizens">the citizens</persName> on their behalf, still more irritated <persName id="#the_citizens">the citizens</persName>, in that by depriving them not only of the opportunity of receiving money, but even of conferring a favour, he rendered <persName id="#the_people">the people</persName> at once poor and dishonoured.
In addition to this, as Cato had neither any persuasive manners in canvassing for himself, but wished to maintain the dignity of his life in his character rather than to add to it that of the consulship by shaking hands with <persName id="#the_electors">the electors</persName>, and as he would not allow <persName id="#his_friends">his friends</persName> to do the things by which the mass are taken and gained over, he lost the office.
L.
Though the matter caused not only to those who failed, but to <persName id="#their_friends">their friends</persName> and kin a certain degree of shame and depression and sorrow for many days, <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> bore what had happened with so little concern, that after anointing himself in the Campus he exercised at ball, and again after dinner, according to his wont, he went down into the Forum without his shoes and tunic, and walked about with <persName id="#his_intimates">his intimates</persName>.
But Cicero blames him, that when the times required <persName id="#such_a_magistrate">such a magistrate</persName>, he used no exertion nor tried to gain the favour of <persName id="#the_people">the people</persName> by friendly intercourse with them, but for the future ceased to make any effort and gave up the contest, though he was again <persName id="#a_candidate">a candidate</persName> for the praetorship.
Cato, however, said, that he lost the praetorship not by the real will of <persName id="#the_majority">the majority</persName>, but because they were forced or corrupted; whereas in the voting for the consulship, in which there was no foul play, he further perceived that he had displeased <persName id="#the_people">the people</persName> by his manners, which it was not the part of <persName id="#a_man">a man</persName> of sense to change in order to please others, nor, if he still kept to the like manners, to subject himself to the like treatment.
LI.
When <persName id="#caesar">Caesar</persName> had attacked warlike nations and had conquered them with great hazard, and when it was the opinion that he had fallen upon the <personGrp id="#germans">Germans</personGrp> even after a truce had been made, and had destroyed three hundred thousand of them, the rest indeed were promising to <persName id="#the_people">the people</persName> to offer sacrifices for the victory, but <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> urged that they should give up <persName id="#caesar">Caesar</persName> to those who had been wronged, and should not turn the guilt upon themselves nor allow it to fall on the state.
"However," said he, "let us still sacrifice to <persName id="#the_gods">the gods</persName>, that they do not turn their vengeance for the madness and desperation of <persName id="#the_commander">the commander</persName> upon <persName id="#the_soldiers">the soldiers</persName>, and that they spare the city."
Upon this <persName id="#caesar">Caesar</persName> wrote and sent a letter to the Senate; and when the letter had been read, which contained much abuse of Cato and many charges against him, <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> got up, and not under the influence of passion or personal animosity, but as if it were on good consideration and due preparation, showed that the charges against him were in the nature of abuse and insult, and were pure trifling and mockery on Caesar's part.
Then taking hold of all <persName id="#caesar">Caesar</persName>'s measures from the first, and unveiling all his plans, not as if he were <persName id="#an_enemy">an enemy</persName>, but a fellow conspirator and participator, he proved to them that they had no reason to fear <persName id="#the_sons">the sons</persName> of the <personGrp id="#britons">Britons</personGrp> nor yet the <personGrp id="#celts">Celts</personGrp>, but <persName id="#caesar">Caesar</persName> himself, if they were prudent; and he so worked on and excited them that <persName id="#the_friends">the friends</persName> of <persName id="#caesar">Caesar</persName> repented of having read the letter in the Senate, and so given <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> an opportunity of making a fair statement and true charges.
Nothing, however, was done, but it was merely said that it would be well for <persName id="#a_successor">a successor</persName> to <persName id="#caesar">Caesar</persName> to be appointed.
But when <persName id="#caesar's_friends">Caesar's friends</persName> required that <persName id="#pompeius">Pompeius</persName> also should lay down his arms and give up his provinces, or that <persName id="#caesar">Caesar</persName> should not, <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> cried out, that now what he foretold them had come to pass, and that <persName id="#the_man">the man</persName> was having recourse to force and was openly employing the power which he had got by deceiving and gulling the state; yet <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> could do nothing out of doors, because <persName id="#the_people">the people</persName> all along wished <persName id="#caesar">Caesar</persName> to have the chief power, and he found the Senate ready to assent to his measures, but afraid of <persName id="#the_people">the people</persName>.
LII.
But when Ariminum was captured, and news came that <persName id="#caesar">Caesar</persName> with <persName id="#his_army">his army</persName> was advancing against the city, then indeed <persName id="#all_men">all men</persName> turned their eyes on <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName>, <persName id="#both_the_people">both the people</persName> and <persName id="#pompeius">Pompeius</persName>, as <persName id="#the_only_man">the only man</persName> who from the first had foreseen and who had first clearly shown the designs of <persName id="#caesar">Caesar</persName>.
Accordingly <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> said, "Men, if any among you had listened to what I had all along been foretelling and advising, you would neither have to fear <persName id="#a_single_man">a single man</persName> now, nor would you have to rest all your hopes on <persName id="#a_single_man">a single man</persName>."
Upon <persName id="#pompeius">Pompeius</persName> saying that <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> had indeed spoken more like <persName id="#a_prophet">a prophet</persName>, but that he had acted more like <persName id="#a_friend">a friend</persName>, <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> advised the Senate to place affairs in the hands of Pompeius alone, for it was the business of those who caused great evils to put an end to them.
Now as Pompeius had not a force in readiness, and he saw that <persName id="#the_troops">the troops</persName> which he was then levying had no zeal, he left <personGrp id="#rome">Rome</personGrp>.
Cato having determined to follow <persName id="#pompeius">Pompeius</persName> in his flight, sent <persName id="#his_younger_son">his younger son</persName> into the country of the <personGrp id="#bruttii">Bruttii</personGrp> to <persName id="#munatius">Munatius</persName> for safe keeping, but <persName id="#the_elder">the elder</persName> he took with him.
And as <persName id="#his_household">his household</persName> and <persName id="#daughters">daughters</persName> required some one to look after them, he took again <persName id="#marcia">Marcia</persName>, who was now <persName id="#a_widow">a widow</persName> with a large estate, for <persName id="#hortensius">Hortensius</persName> at his death had made her his heir.
It was with reference to this that <persName id="#caesar">Caesar</persName> vented most abuse on <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName>, and charged him with covetousness and making a traffic of his marriage; for why should he give up <persName id="#his_wife">his wife</persName>, said <persName id="#caesar">Caesar</persName>, if he still wanted one, or why should he take her back, if he did not want one? if it was not that from the first <persName id="#the_woman">the woman</persName> was put as a bait in the way of Hortensius, and <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> gave her up when she was young that he might have her back when she was rich.
Now, in reply to these charges, this from Euripides suffices:-- "First then what can't be said, for of this kind I deem thy so call'd cowardice, O Hercules."
For to accuse <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> of filthy lucre is like upbraiding <personGrp id="#hercules">Hercules</personGrp> with cowardice.
But whether the matter of the marriage was not well in other respects is a thing for inquiry.
However, <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> did espouse <persName id="#marcia">Marcia</persName>, and intrusting to <persName id="#her_his_family">her his family</persName> and <persName id="#daughters">daughters</persName>, hurried after <persName id="#pompeius">Pompeius</persName>.
LIII.
From that day it is said that <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> never cut the hair of his head or beard, nor put on a chaplet, but maintained till his death the same outward signs of sorrow and depression of spirits and grief over the misfortunes of his country, just the same when <persName id="#his_party">his party</persName> was victorious and when it was vanquished.
At that time having got by lot <personGrp id="#sicily">Sicily</personGrp> as his province, he crossed over to <personGrp id="#syracuse">Syracuse</personGrp>, and on hearing that <placeName id="#asinius_pollio">Asinius Pollio</placeName> had arrived from <persName id="#the_enemy">the enemy</persName> with a large force at <persName id="#messene">Messene</persName>, he sent to him to demand the reason of his coming.
But <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> in turn being asked for the reason of the change in affairs, and having heard that Pompeius had completely deserted <personGrp id="#italy">Italy</personGrp> and was encamped in <personGrp id="#dyrrachium">Dyrrachium</personGrp>, he said that there was great perplexity and uncertainty in matters appertaining to <persName id="#the_gods">the gods</persName>.
Pompeius, who had always been invincible while he was doing what was not honest or just, now when he wished to save his country and fight in defence of liberty, was deserted by his good fortune.
As to Asinius, he said that he was able to drive him out of <personGrp id="#sicily">Sicily</personGrp>, but as another greater force was coming against him, he did not choose to ruin the island by a war; and after advising the <personGrp id="#syracusans">Syracusans</personGrp> to join <persName id="#the_victorious_party">the victorious party</persName> and to take care of themselves, he sailed away.
When he came to <persName id="#pompeius">Pompeius</persName>, he kept steadily to one opinion, to prolong the war, for he expected some terms of reconciliation and did not wish that the state should be worsted in a battle and suffer from itself the extreme of sufferings by having its fate determined by the sword.
And he persuaded <persName id="#pompeius">Pompeius</persName> and <persName id="#his_council">his council</persName> to other determinations akin to these, neither to plunder any city that was subject to the <personGrp id="#romans">Romans</personGrp>, nor to put to death any <personGrp id="#roman">Roman</personGrp> except on the field of battle; and he gained good opinion and brought over many to the side of Pompeius, who were pleased with his moderation and mildness.
LIV.
Being sent to <placeName id="#asia">Asia</placeName> to help those there who were collecting vessels and <persName id="#an_army">an army</persName>, he took with him <persName id="#his_sister">his sister</persName> <personGrp id="#servilia">Servilia</personGrp> and <persName id="#her_young_child">her young child</persName> by <personGrp id="#lucullus">Lucullus</personGrp>.
For Servilia, who was now <persName id="#a_widow">a widow</persName>, followed <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName>, and she removed much of the evil report about her licentious conduct by voluntarily subjecting herself to the guardianship of Cato and his wanderings and mode of life.
But <persName id="#caesar">Caesar</persName> did not spare his abuse of <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> even with respect to Servilia.
However as it seems <persName id="#the_generals">the generals</persName> of Pompeius did not want the assistance of <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> at all; and after persuading the <personGrp id="#rhodians">Rhodians</personGrp> to join the side of Pompeius and leaving Servilia and <persName id="#the_child">the child</persName> there, he returned to Pompeius, who had already a splendid military force and a naval power with him.
Here indeed Pompeius appeared most clearly to show his mind; for at first he intended to give to <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> the command of the ships, and the fighting vessels were not fewer than five hundred, and <persName id="#the_liburnian_and_spy_ships">the Liburnian and spy ships</persName> and open boats were very numerous: but having soon perceived, or it having been hinted to him by <persName id="#his_friends">his friends</persName>, that it was the one chief thing in all the policy of <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> to liberate his country, and that if he should have the command of so great a force, the very day on which they should defeat <persName id="#caesar">Caesar</persName>, <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> would require Pompeius also to lay down his arms and to follow the laws, he changed his mind though he had already spoken with him, and he appointed <personGrp id="#bibulus_commander">Bibulus commander</personGrp> of the ships.
Yet he found not <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName>'s zeal dulled by this; for it is told that when <persName id="#pompeius">Pompeius</persName> was urging <persName id="#his_troops">his troops</persName> to a battle before <persName id="#dyrrachium">Dyrrachium</persName> and bidding each of <persName id="#the_commanders">the commanders</persName> say something and to encourage <persName id="#the_men">the men</persName>, <persName id="#the_soldiers">the soldiers</persName> heard them with listlessness and silence; but when <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName>, after the rest, had gone through all the topics derived from philosophy that were suitable to the occasion to be said about liberty and virtue, and death and good fame, with great emotion on his part, and finally addressed himself to invoke <persName id="#the_gods">the gods</persName> as being there present and watching over the struggle on behalf of their country, there was so loud an acclamation and so great a movement in <persName id="#the_whole_army">the whole army</persName> thus excited, that <persName id="#all_the_commanders">all the commanders</persName> hastened to the contest full of hopes.
<persName id="#the_soldiers">The soldiers</persName> of Pompeius routed and defeated <persName id="#the_enemy">the enemy</persName>, but <persName id="#the_daemon">the daemon</persName> of <persName id="#caesar">Caesar</persName> prevented the completion of the victory by taking advantage of the caution of Pompeius and his want of confidence in his success.
Now this is told in the Life of Pompeius.
But while all were rejoicing and magnifying the victory, <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> wept for his country and bewailed the love of power that brought destruction and misfortune with it, when he saw that <persName id="#many_brave_citizens">many brave citizens</persName> had fallen by the hands of one another.
LV.
When <persName id="#pompeius">Pompeius</persName> in order to pursue <persName id="#caesar">Caesar</persName> broke up his camp to march into <personGrp id="#thessaly">Thessaly</personGrp>, he left at <persName id="#dyrrachium">Dyrrachium</persName> a great quantity of arms and stores, and <persName id="#many_kinsmen">many kinsmen</persName> and <persName id="#friends">friends</persName>, and he appointed <persName id="#cato_commander">Cato commander</persName> and <persName id="#guardian">guardian</persName> over <persName id="#all_with_fifteen_cohorts">all with fifteen cohorts</persName>, both because he trusted and feared <persName id="#the_man">the man</persName>.
For if he were defeated, he considered that <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> would be his surest support; but that if he were victorious, <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> would not, if he were present, let him manage matters as he chose.
<persName id="#many_men">Many men</persName> of rank also were left behind in <persName id="#dyrrachium">Dyrrachium</persName> with <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName>.
When the defeat at Pharsalus took place, <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> resolved that if <persName id="#pompeius">Pompeius</persName> were dead, he would take over to <personGrp id="#italy">Italy</personGrp> those who were with him, and himself would live an exile as far from the tyranny as possible; but if <persName id="#pompeius">Pompeius</persName> were alive, that he would by all means keep together the force for him.
Accordingly having crossed over to <persName id="#cercyra">Cercyra</persName>, where the navy was, he proposed to give up the command to Cicero, who was a consular, while he was only of praetorian rank; but when Cicero would not accept the command and set off for <personGrp id="#italy">Italy</personGrp>, <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> observing that <persName id="#pompeius">Pompeius</persName> through his stubborn self-will and unreasonable temper was desirous of punishing those who were sailing away, privately admonished and pacified him, by which <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> manifestly saved Cicero from death and secured the safety of the rest.
LVI.
<persName id="#conjecturing">Conjecturing</persName> that <persName id="#pompeius_magnus">Pompeius Magnus</persName> would make his escape to <personGrp id="#egypt">Egypt</personGrp> or to <personGrp id="#libya">Libya</personGrp>, and being in haste to join him, <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> with all whom he had about him weighed anchor and set sail after permitting all those to go away or stay behind who were not ready to accompany him.
He reached <personGrp id="#libya">Libya</personGrp>, and coasting along he fell in with Sextus, <persName id="#the_younger_son">the younger son</persName> of <persName id="#pompeius">Pompeius</persName>, who reported to him <persName id="#his_father's_death">his father's death</persName> in <personGrp id="#egypt">Egypt</personGrp>.
Now they were all much troubled, and no one after the death of <persName id="#pompeius">Pompeius</persName> would obey <persName id="#any_other_commander">any other commander</persName> while <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> was present.
Wherefore <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName>, out of respect to those who were with him, and because he had not heart to desert and leave in difficulties <persName id="#the_brave_men">the brave men</persName> who had given proof of their fidelity, undertook the command and went along the coast till he came to <persName id="#cyrene">Cyrene</persName>; for <persName id="#the_people">the people</persName> received him though a few days before they had shut out <personGrp id="#labienus">Labienus</personGrp>.
Upon hearing that <personGrp id="#scipio">Scipio</personGrp>, <persName id="#the_father">the father</persName>-in-law of <persName id="#pompeius">Pompeius</persName>, had been well received by King <persName id="#juba">Juba</persName>, and that Varus Attius, who had been appointed governor of <personGrp id="#libya">Libya</personGrp> by Pompeius, was with them with a force, he set out by land in the winter season, having got together a number of asses to carry water, and driving along with him a quantity of cattle, and also taking chariots and <persName id="#the_people">the people</persName> called Psylli, who cure the bites of serpents by sucking out the poison with their mouths, and deaden and soothe the serpents themselves by charming them with music.
Though the march was seven days in succession, <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> led at the head of <persName id="#his_men">his men</persName> without using horse or beast of burden.
And he continued to sup in a sitting posture from the day that he heard of the defeat at Pharsalus, and he added this further sign of his sorrow, never to lie down except when he was sleeping.
Having spent the winter in <personGrp id="#libya">Libya</personGrp> he led forth <persName id="#his_army">his army</persName>; and <persName id="#the_men">the men</persName> were near ten thousand.
LVII.
Matters were in bad plight between <personGrp id="#scipio">Scipio</personGrp> and Varus, for in consequence of their disagreement and disunion they were secretly trying to win the favour of <persName id="#juba">Juba</persName>, who was intolerable for the arrogance of his temper and his haughtiness by reason of his wealth and power.
When he was going to have his first interview with <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName>, <persName id="#juba">Juba</persName> placed his seat between the seats of <personGrp id="#scipio">Scipio</personGrp> and <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName>.
However, when <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> observed it, he took up his seat and moved it to the other side so as to leave <persName id="#scipio">Scipio</persName> in the middle, though <persName id="#scipio">Scipio</persName> was <persName id="#his_enemy">his enemy</persName>, and had published a certain writing which contained abuse of <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName>.
This, indeed, <persName id="#people">people</persName> make no account of; but they blame <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> that in <personGrp id="#sicily">Sicily</personGrp> he placed Philostratus in the middle, as he was walking about with him, to do honour to philosophy.
On this occasion, however, he checked <persName id="#juba">Juba</persName>, who had all but made <persName id="#scipio">Scipio</persName> and Varus <persName id="#his_satraps">his satraps</persName>, and he reconciled them.
Though all invited <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> to the command, and Scipio and Varus were the first to surrender and give it up to him, he said that he would not break the laws in defence of which they were fighting against him who broke them, nor would he place himself, who was <persName id="#a_propraetor">a propraetor</persName>, before <persName id="#a_proconsul">a proconsul</persName> who was present.
For <persName id="#scipio">Scipio</persName> had been appointed proconsul, and <persName id="#the_majority">the majority</persName>, on account of the name, had confidence that they should be successful, if a <personGrp id="#scipio">Scipio</personGrp> commanded in <personGrp id="#libya">Libya</personGrp>.
LVIII.
However when <personGrp id="#scipio">Scipio</personGrp> immediately on receiving the command, wished to please <persName id="#juba">Juba</persName> by putting to death <persName id="#all_the_people">all the people</persName> of <personGrp id="#utica">Utica</personGrp> who were capable of bearing arms, and to dig down the city, because it favoured <persName id="#caesar">Caesar</persName>, <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> would not endure this, but with adjurations and loud cries in <persName id="#the_council">the council</persName> and by appealing to <persName id="#the_gods">the gods</persName> he with difficulty rescued <persName id="#the_people">the people</persName> from their cruelty; and partly at the request of <persName id="#the_citizens">the citizens</persName> of <personGrp id="#utica">Utica</personGrp> and partly at the instance of <personGrp id="#scipio">Scipio</personGrp>, he undertook to keep <persName id="#guard">guard</persName> in the city, that it should not either involuntarily or voluntarily join <persName id="#caesar">Caesar</persName>.
For the place was in all respects advantageous, and defensible by those who held it; and it was strengthened still more by <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName>.
For he brought abundance of corn into the city, and he strengthened the walls by raising towers, and making strong ditches and palisado-work in front of the city.
To <persName id="#the_people">the people</persName> of <personGrp id="#utica">Utica</personGrp> who were able to bear arms he assigned the palisado-work as their quarter, and made them give up their arms to him; but he kept the rest in the city, and took great care that they should not be wronged and should suffer no harm from the <personGrp id="#romans">Romans</personGrp>.
He also sent out a great quantity of arms, supplies and grain to those in camp, and altogether he made the city the storehouse for the war.
But the advice which he gave <persName id="#pompeius">Pompeius</persName> before, and gave <persName id="#scipio">Scipio</persName> then, not to fight with <persName id="#a_man">a man</persName> of a warlike turn and great ability, but to take advantage of time which wastes all the vigour wherein the strength of tyranny lies, <persName id="#scipio">Scipio</persName> through self-will despised; and on one occasion he wrote to <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> upbraiding him with cowardice, in that he was not content to sit down within a city and walls, but would not even let others boldly use their own judgment as opportunity offered.
To this <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> replied, that he was ready to take <persName id="#the_legionary_soldiers">the legionary soldiers</persName> and <persName id="#horsemen">horsemen</persName> whom he had brought into <personGrp id="#libya">Libya</personGrp>, and carry them over to <personGrp id="#italy">Italy</personGrp>, and so make <persName id="#caesar">Caesar</persName> change his place and to turn him from them to himself.
And when <persName id="#scipio">Scipio</persName> mocked at this also, it was clear that <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> was much annoyed that he had declined the command, for he saw that <persName id="#scipio">Scipio</persName> would neither conduct the war well, nor, if he should succeed contrary to expectation, would he behave with moderation to <persName id="#the_citizens">the citizens</persName> in his victory.
Accordingly <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> formed the opinion and mentioned it to some of <persName id="#his_friends">his friends</persName>, that he had no good hopes of the war on account of the inexperience and confidence of <persName id="#the_commanders">the commanders</persName>, but if there should be any good fortune, and <persName id="#caesar">Caesar</persName> should be worsted, he would not stay in <personGrp id="#rome">Rome</personGrp>, and would fly from the harshness and cruelty of <personGrp id="#scipio">Scipio</personGrp>, who was even then uttering dreadful and extravagant threats against many.
But it turned out worse than he expected; and late in the evening there arrived <persName id="#a_messenger">a messenger</persName> from the camp who had been three days on the road, with the news that a great battle had been fought at <persName id="#thapsus">Thapsus</persName> in which their affairs were entirely ruined, that <persName id="#caesar">Caesar</persName> was in possession of the camps, <persName id="#scipio">Scipio</persName> and <persName id="#juba">Juba</persName> had escaped with <persName id="#a_few_men">a few men</persName>, and the rest of <persName id="#the_army">the army</persName> was destroyed.
LIX.
On the arrival of this intelligence, the city, as was natural on the receipt of such news by night and in time of war, nearly lost its reason, and hardly contained itself within the walls; but <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> coming forward, whenever he met with any one running about and calling out, laid hold of him, and cheering him took away the excessive fright and confusion of his alarm, by saying that matters perchance were not so bad as they had been reported, but were magnified by rumour; and so he stayed the tumult.
At daybreak he made proclamation that the three hundred, whom he had as a Senate, and these were <personGrp id="#romans">Romans</personGrp>, and were carrying on business in <personGrp id="#libya">Libya</personGrp> as <persName id="#merchants">merchants</persName> and <persName id="#money-lenders">money-lenders</persName>, should assemble at the temple of <placeName id="#jupiter">Jupiter</placeName>, and also <persName id="#all_the_roman_senators">all the Roman senators</persName> who were present and <persName id="#their_sons">their sons</persName>.
While they were still assembling, Cato advanced, without hurry and with a tranquil countenance, as if nothing new had happened, holding a book in his hand, which he was reading; and this was a register of the military engines, arms, corn, bows, and <persName id="#legionary_soldiers">legionary soldiers</persName>.
When they had come together, beginning with the three hundred, and commending at some length the zeal and fidelity which they had displayed in aiding with their means and persons and advice, he exhorted them not to let their hopes be destroyed, and not severally to provide for their flight or escape.
For, he said, that if they would keep together, Caesar would despise them less if they made resistance, and would spare them more if they asked his mercy.
And he urged them to deliberate about themselves, and that he would not find fault with their deciding either way, and if they should be disposed to turn to the fortunate side, he should attribute the change to necessity; but if they preferred to oppose the danger and to undertake the hazard in defence of liberty, he should not only commend them, but admire their virtue, and make himself their commander and fellow-combatant, till they had tried the last fortune of their country, which was not <personGrp id="#utica">Utica</personGrp> or Adrumetum only, but <personGrp id="#rome">Rome</personGrp>, that had often by her might recovered from greater falls.
And they had many grounds for safety and security; and <persName id="#chief">chief</persName> of all, that they were warring against <persName id="#a_man">a man</persName> who was pulled in many directions by the circumstances of the times, for <personGrp id="#iberia">Iberia</personGrp> had gone over to Pompeius the young, and <personGrp id="#rome">Rome</personGrp> herself had not yet altogether received the bit for want of being used to it, but was impatient of suffering and ready to rise up collected upon every change, and danger was not a thing to fly from, but they should take as a pattern <persName id="#the_enemy">the enemy</persName>, who was not sparing of his life for accomplishing the greatest wrongs, and for whom the uncertainty of the war had not the same result as for them, to whom it would bring the happiest life, if they were successful, and the most glorious death if they failed.
However, he said they ought to deliberate by themselves, and he joined them in praying that in consideration of their former virtue and zeal what they resolved might be for the best.
LX.
When <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> had spoken to this effect, some of them indeed were brought to confidence by his words; but the greater part seeing his fearlessness and noble and generous temper, nearly forgot present circumstances, and considering him alone as <persName id="#an_invincible_leader">an invincible leader</persName> and superior to all fortune, prayed him to use their persons and property and arms as he judged best, for they said it was better to die in obedience to him than to save their lives by betraying such virtue.
On <persName id="#a_certain_person">a certain person</persName> observing that they should declare freedom to <persName id="#the_slaves">the slaves</persName>, and most of them assenting to this, <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> said he would not do so, for it was not lawful nor yet right; but if <persName id="#the_masters">the masters</persName> were ready to give up <persName id="#their_slaves">their slaves</persName>, they should receive those who were of military age.
Many offers were made, and <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName>, after telling them to enrol <persName id="#every_man">every man</persName> who was willing, retired.
Shortly after there came to him letters from <persName id="#juba">Juba</persName> and <personGrp id="#scipio">Scipio</personGrp>; from <persName id="#juba">Juba</persName>, who was hid in a mountain with <persName id="#a_few_men">a few men</persName>, asking him what he had resolved to do; and that if <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> left <personGrp id="#utica">Utica</personGrp> he would wait for him, and if he stood a siege he would come to aid him with <persName id="#an_army">an army</persName>; from <personGrp id="#scipio">Scipio</personGrp>, who was in a vessel off a certain point not far from <personGrp id="#utica">Utica</personGrp>, and waiting with the same views.
LXI.
Accordingly <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> determined to detain <persName id="#the_letter-carriers">the letter-carriers</persName> till he had confirmed the resolution of the three hundred.
For <persName id="#the_senators">the senators</persName> were zealous, and immediately manumitted <persName id="#their_slaves">their slaves</persName>, and set about arming them.
But with respect to the three hundred, inasmuch as they were <persName id="#men">men</persName> engaged in maritime affairs and money lending, and had the chief part of their substance in <persName id="#slaves">slaves</persName>, the words of <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> stood no long time in them, but oozed out, just as bodies which have a great degree of rarity easily receive heat and again part with it, being cooled when the fire is removed; in like manner <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName>, while they saw him, fanned the flame and warmed <persName id="#those_men">those men</persName>; but when they began to reflect by themselves, the fear of <persName id="#caesar">Caesar</persName> drove out of them all regard to <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> and to honour.
"Who are we," said they, "and who is <persName id="#the_man">the man</persName> whose commands we are refusing to obey? Is not this <persName id="#caesar">Caesar</persName>, to whom the whole power of the <personGrp id="#romans">Romans</personGrp> has been transferred? and not one of us is a <personGrp id="#scipio">Scipio</personGrp>, nor a Pompeius, nor a Cato.
But at a time when <persName id="#all_men">all men</persName> by reason of fear are humbled in mind more than is fitting, at such a time shall we fight in defence of the liberty of the <personGrp id="#romans">Romans</personGrp>, and contend in <personGrp id="#utica">Utica</personGrp> against <persName id="#a_man">a man</persName> before whom <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> with <persName id="#pompeius_magnus">Pompeius Magnus</persName> fled and gave up <personGrp id="#italy">Italy</personGrp>; and shall we manumit <persName id="#our_slaves">our slaves</persName> to oppose <persName id="#caesar">Caesar</persName>, we who have only as much freedom as he shall choose to give? <persName id="#no,_even_yet,_miserable_wretches">No, even yet, miserable wretches</persName>, let us know our own weakness, and deprecate <persName id="#the_conqueror">the conqueror</persName>, and send persons to supplicate him."
This was what the most moderate among the three hundred recommended; but <persName id="#the_majority">the majority</persName> were forming a design on the senatorial class, with the hope that, if they seized them, they would pacify <persName id="#caesar">Caesar</persName>'s rage against themselves.
LXII.
Though Cato suspected the change, he took no notice of it.
However he wrote to <persName id="#scipio">Scipio</persName> and <persName id="#juba">Juba</persName> to tell them to keep away from <personGrp id="#utica">Utica</personGrp>, because he distrusted the three hundred, and he sent off <persName id="#the_letter-carriers">the letter-carriers</persName>.
But <persName id="#the_horsemen">the horsemen</persName> who had escaped from the battle, no contemptible number, riding up to <personGrp id="#utica">Utica</personGrp>, sent to <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> <persName id="#three_men">three men</persName>, who did not bring the same message from all; for <persName id="#one_party">one party</persName> was bent on going to <persName id="#juba">Juba</persName>, another wished to join <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName>, and a third was afraid of entering <personGrp id="#utica">Utica</personGrp>.
Cato on hearing this ordered <persName id="#marcus_rubrius">Marcus Rubrius</persName> to observe the three hundred and quietly to receive the registrations of those who manumitted <persName id="#their_slaves">their slaves</persName> without forcing any one; and himself taking <persName id="#the_senatorial_men">the senatorial men</persName> went out of <personGrp id="#utica">Utica</personGrp>, and meeting with <persName id="#the_commanders">the commanders</persName> of <persName id="#the_cavalry">the cavalry</persName> he besought them not to betray <persName id="#so_many_roman_senators">so many Roman senators</persName>, nor to choose <persName id="#juba">Juba</persName> for <persName id="#their_commander">their commander</persName> in place of <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> but to secure their own safety and that of the rest by coming into a city which could not be taken by storm, and contained both corn and other resources for many years.
<persName id="#the_senatorial_men">The senatorial men</persName> joined in this prayer and wept; and <persName id="#the_commanders">the commanders</persName> conferred with <persName id="#the_cavalry">the cavalry</persName>, while <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> sat down on a mound with <persName id="#the_senatorial_men">the senatorial men</persName> and waited for the answer.
LXIII.
In the meantime <persName id="#rubrius">Rubrius</persName> came in a passion, charging the three hundred with great disorder and tumult, inasmuch, as they were falling off and disturbing the city.
On which the rest, altogether despairing, fell to weeping and lamentation, but <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> attempted to cheer them, and sent to the three hundred and bade them wait.
But <persName id="#the_representatives">the representatives</persName> on the part of <persName id="#the_horsemen">the horsemen</persName> came with no reasonable requisitions: for they said that they neither wanted <persName id="#juba">Juba</persName> for <persName id="#their_pay-master">their pay-master</persName>, nor were they afraid of <persName id="#caesar">Caesar</persName> if they had <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> to command them, but it was a dangerous thing to shut themselves up with <persName id="#the_citizens">the citizens</persName> of <personGrp id="#utica">Utica</personGrp>, who were Phnicians and an inconstant people; and if they should keep quiet now, they would set upon them and betray them, when <persName id="#caesar">Caesar</persName> came.
If then <persName id="#any_man">any man</persName> wanted their aid in war and their presence, he must eject or kill <persName id="#all_the_people">all the people</persName> of <personGrp id="#utica">Utica</personGrp>, and then invite them into a city free from <persName id="#enemies">enemies</persName> and <persName id="#barbarians">barbarians</persName>.
Cato considered this to be an excessively savage and barbarous proposal, but he answered mildly and said that he would consult with the three hundred.
When he had returned into the city he found <persName id="#the_men">the men</persName> no longer making pretexts or evasions out of respect to him, but openly complaining that any one should force them to fight with <persName id="#caesar">Caesar</persName> when they were neither able nor willing.
Some even whispered with respect to <persName id="#the_senatorial_men">the senatorial men</persName>, that they ought to keep them in the city, since <persName id="#caesar">Caesar</persName> was near.
Cato let this pass as if he did not hear it, and indeed he was somewhat deaf; but when one came up to him and reported that <persName id="#the_horsemen">the horsemen</persName> were going away, <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName>, fearing that the three hundred might do something desperate to <persName id="#the_senatorial_men">the senatorial men</persName>, got up with <persName id="#his_friends">his friends</persName> and set out walking; but observing that they had already advanced some distance, he seized a horse and rode to them.
<persName id="#the_horsemen">The horsemen</persName> were glad to see him approach, and received him and urged him to save himself with them.
Then it is said that <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> even shed tears, beseeching on behalf of <persName id="#the_senatorial_men">the senatorial men</persName> and holding forth his hands, and turning back the horses of some and laying hold of their arms, until he prevailed on them to abide there for that day at least, and secure <persName id="#the_senatorial_men">the senatorial men</persName> in their flight.
LXIV.
When <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> arrived with <persName id="#the_horsemen">the horsemen</persName>, and had posted some at the gates, and had delivered the citadel to others to watch, the three hundred, who were afraid that they should be punished for their change, sent to <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> and prayed him by all means to come to them.
But <persName id="#the_senatorial_men">the senatorial men</persName> crowding round him would not let him go, and they declared that they would not give up <persName id="#their_guardian">their guardian</persName> and <persName id="#saviour">saviour</persName> to <persName id="#faithless_men">faithless men</persName> and <persName id="#traitors">traitors</persName>.
For a most lively perception, as it appears, and affection and admiration of <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName>'s virtue had been implanted in all alike who were in <personGrp id="#utica">Utica</personGrp>, inasmuch as nothing spurious or deceitful was mingled with what he did.
And as <persName id="#the_man">the man</persName> had long resolved to kill himself, he laboured with prodigious toil, and had care and pain on behalf of others, in order that after placing all in safety he might be released from life.
For his resolution to die was no secret, though he said nothing.
Accordingly he complied with the wish of the three hundred after comforting <persName id="#the_senatorial_men">the senatorial men</persName>, and he went alone to the three hundred, who thanked him, and prayed him to employ them and trust them in everything else, and if they are not <persName id="#catos">Catos</persName>, and not capable of the lofty mind of <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName>, he should have pity on their weakness; and as they had determined to supplicate <persName id="#caesar">Caesar</persName> and to send to him, on <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName>'s behalf chiefly and for him first of all they would prefer their prayer; and if they could not prevail on Caesar, neither would they receive the grace if it were offered to themselves, but so long as they breathed would fight for him.
In reply to this <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> commended their good intentions, but said that they ought for their own safety's sake to send quickly, and not to offer any petition on his behalf, for entreaty belonged to the vanquished, and deprecation of vengeance to those who were <persName id="#wrongdoers">wrongdoers</persName>; that he had not only been unvanquished all through life, but that he was victorious as far as he chose to be, and had the superiority over <persName id="#caesar">Caesar</persName> in things honourable and just, and that <persName id="#caesar">Caesar</persName> was <persName id="#the_party">the party</persName> who was captured and conquered; for what he used to deny that he was doing against his country long ago, he was now convicted of and detected therein.
LXV.
Having thus spoken to the three hundred he went away, and hearing that Caesar at the head of <persName id="#all_his_army">all his army</persName> was already on his march, "Ha!" said he, "he considers that he has to deal with <persName id="#men">men</persName>;" and turning to <persName id="#the_senators">the senators</persName> he urged them not to delay, but to make their escape while <persName id="#the_horsemen">the horsemen</persName> were still staying there.
He also closed the gates, except one that led to the sea, where he assigned vessels to those under his command and preserved order by stopping wrong-doing and settling disturbances, and supplying with stores those who were ill provided.
And when <persName id="#marcus_octavius">Marcus Octavius</persName> with <persName id="#two_legions">two legions</persName> had encamped near, and had sent a message to <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName>, in which he called on <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> to come to some terms with him about the command, <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> gave him no answer, but he said to <persName id="#his_friends">his friends</persName>, "Do we wonder why our affairs are ruined, when we see that love of power abides among us even when we are in the midst of ruin?" In the mean time hearing that <persName id="#the_horsemen">the horsemen</persName>, as they were leaving the city, were pillaging and plundering <persName id="#the_people">the people</persName> of <personGrp id="#utica">Utica</personGrp>, as if their property was booty, <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> hurried to them as fast as he could run, and took the plunder from the first that he met with, and the rest made haste to throw it away or set it down on the ground, and all of them for very shame retired in silence and with downcast looks.
Cato having called together <persName id="#the_people">the people</persName> of <personGrp id="#utica">Utica</personGrp> in the city, entreated them not to irritate <persName id="#caesar">Caesar</persName> against the three hundred, but to unite altogether to secure their safety.
Then again betaking himself to the sea he inspected the persons who were embarking, and <persName id="#all_his_friends">all his friends</persName> and acquaintance whom he could persuade to go away, he embraced and accompanied to the shore.
But he did not recommend <persName id="#his_son">his son</persName> to take shipping, nor did he think it his duty to turn him from his purpose of sticking to <persName id="#his_father">his father</persName>.
There was one <persName id="#statyllius">Statyllius</persName>, in years a young man, but one who aimed at being resolute in character and <persName id="#an_imitator">an imitator</persName> of the indifference of <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName>.
<persName id="#this_man">This man</persName> <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> entreated to embark, for he was notoriously <persName id="#a_hater">a hater</persName> of Caesar; and-when he would not go, <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> looking on <persName id="#apollonides">Apollonides</persName> the Stoic and <persName id="#demetrius">Demetrius</persName> the <personGrp id="#peripatetic">Peripatetic</personGrp> said--"It is your business to soften <persName id="#this_stubborn_man">this stubborn man</persName> and to fashion him to his own interests."
But <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> himself was busied all the night and the greatest part of the following day in assisting the rest in making their escape and helping those who wanted his aid.
LXVI.
When <persName id="#lucius_caaesar">Lucius Caaesar</persName>, who was <persName id="#a_kinsman">a kinsman</persName> of <persName id="#caesar">Caesar</persName>, and about to go to him as <persName id="#ambassador">ambassador</persName> on behalf of the three hundred, urged Cato to help him in devising some plausible speech which he should employ on behalf of the three hundred, "for on thy behalf," he continued, "it is becoming for me to touch the hands and to fall down at the knees of <persName id="#caesar">Caesar</persName>," <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> would not allow him to do this, and said, "For my part, if I wished to save my life by Caesar's favour, I ought to go to him myself.
But I do not choose to thank <persName id="#a_tyrant">a tyrant</persName> for his illegal acts; and he acts illegally in sparing as master those whom he has no right to lord it over.
However, if you please, let us consider how you shall get pardon for the three hundred."
After talking with <persName id="#lucius">Lucius</persName> on this matter he presented <persName id="#his_son">his son</persName> and <persName id="#his_friends">his friends</persName> to him as he was departing, and after accompanying him some distance and taking leave of him he returned home, and then calling together <persName id="#his_son">his son</persName> and <persName id="#his_friends">his friends</persName> he spoke on many subjects, among which he forbade <persName id="#his_son">his son</persName> to meddle in political matters, for, he said, circumstances no longer allowed him to act as befitted a <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName>, and to act otherwise was base.
At evening he went to the bath.
While he was bathing, he remembered <persName id="#statyllius">Statyllius</persName>, and calling out aloud he said, "<persName id="#apollonides">Apollonides</persName>, have you sent <persName id="#statyllius">Statyllius</persName> away, and brought him down from his stubborn temper, and has <persName id="#the_man">the man</persName> gone without even taking leave of us?" "By no means," replied <persName id="#apollonides">Apollonides</persName>, "though we said much to him, but he is lofty and immovable and says he will stay and do whatever you do."
On this they say that <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> smiled and replied, "Well, this will soon be shown."
LXVII.
After taking the bath he supped in <persName id="#much_company">much company</persName>, still sitting as his fashion had been since the battle, for he never reclined except when he was sleeping; and there were at supper with him <persName id="#all_his_friends">all his friends</persName> and <persName id="#the_magistrates">the magistrates</persName> of <personGrp id="#utica">Utica</personGrp>.
After supper the drinking went on with much gaiety and enjoyment, one philosophical subject after another taking its turn, till at last the enquiry came round to the so-called paradoxes of the Stoics, that <persName id="#the_good_man">the good man</persName> alone is free, and that all the bad are <persName id="#slaves">slaves</persName>.
<personGrp id="#hereupon">Hereupon</personGrp> the <placeName id="#peripatetic">Peripatetic</placeName> making objections, as one might expect, <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> broke in with great vehemence, and with a loud tone and harsh voice maintained his discourse at great length, and displayed wonderful energy, so that no one failed to observe that he had resolved to end his life and relieve himself from present troubles.
Wherefore as there was silence and depression of spirits among <persName id="#all_the_company">all the company</persName>, after he had done speaking, with the view of cheering them up and diverting their suspicions, <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> again begun to put questions and to express anxiety about the state of affairs, and his fears for those who had sailed away, and also for those who were going through a waterless and barbarian desert.
LXVIII.
At the end of the entertainment he took his usual walk with <persName id="#his_friends">his friends</persName> after supper, and after giving <persName id="#the_officers">the officers</persName> of the watch the proper orders, he retired to his chamber, but he first embraced <persName id="#his_son">his son</persName> and <persName id="#his_friends">his friends</persName> with more than his usual expression of kindness, which again made them suspect what was going to happen.
On entering his chamber and lying down he took <persName id="#plato">Plato</persName>'s dialogue on the Soul, and when he had gone through the greater part of it, he looked up over his head, and not seeing his sword hanging there, for <persName id="#his_son">his son</persName> had caused it to be taken away while he was at supper, he called <persName id="#a_slave">a slave</persName> and asked who had taken his sword.
<persName id="#the_slave">The slave</persName> made no answer and <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> was again at the book, but after a short interval, as if he were in no haste or hurry, and was merely looking for his sword, he bade <persName id="#the_slave">the slave</persName> bring it.
As there was some delay and <persName id="#nobody">nobody</persName> brought it, after having read the dialogue through he again called <persName id="#his_slaves">his slaves</persName> one by one, and raising his voice demanded his sword; and striking the mouth of one of them with his fist he bruised his hand, being in a great passion and calling out aloud that he was surrendered defenceless to <persName id="#the_enemy">the enemy</persName> by <persName id="#his_son">his son</persName> and <persName id="#his_slaves">his slaves</persName>, till at last <persName id="#his_son">his son</persName> ran in weeping with <persName id="#his_friends">his friends</persName>, and embracing him fell to lamentations and entreaties.
But <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> rising up looked sternly and said, "When and where have I been proved, and without knowing it, to have lost my reason, that no one instructs me or teaches me in the matters wherein I am judged to have determined ill, but I am hindered from using my own reasonings and am deprived of my weapons? Why don't you put <persName id="#your_father">your father</persName> in chains also, <persName id="#generous_son">generous son</persName>, and his hands behind his back, till Caesar shall come and find me unable even to defend myself? For I need not a sword to kill myself, when it is in my power to die by holding my breath for a short time and giving my head a single blow against the wall."
LXIX.
As he said this <persName id="#the_youth">the youth</persName> went out weeping, and all the rest, except <persName id="#demetrius">Demetrius</persName> and <persName id="#apollonides">Apollonides</persName>, to whom when they were left by themselves <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> begun to speak in milder terms, and said, "I suppose you too have resolved by force to keep alive <persName id="#a_man">a man</persName> of my age and to sit here in silence and to watch him, or are you come to prove that it is neither a shocking nor a shameful thing for <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName>, when he has no other way to save his life, to wait for mercy from <persName id="#his_enemy">his enemy</persName>? Why then do you not speak and convince me of this and teach me a new doctrine, that we may cast away those former opinions and reasons in which we lived together, and being made wiser through <persName id="#caesar">Caesar</persName> owe him the greater thanks for it? And yet for my part I have come to no resolve about myself, but it is necessary that when I have resolved I have power to do what I have determined.
And I will deliberate in a manner together with you, deliberating with the reasons which even you in your philosophy follow.
Go away then in good heart and tell <persName id="#my_son">my son</persName> not to force <persName id="#his_father">his father</persName> when he cannot persuade him."
LXX.
Upon this <persName id="#demetrius">Demetrius</persName> and <persName id="#apollonides">Apollonides</persName> without making any reply retired weeping.
The sword was sent in by <persName id="#a_child">a child</persName>, and when <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> received it he drew it and looked at it.
Seeing that the point was entire and the edge preserved, he said, "Now I am <persName id="#my_own_master">my own master</persName>," and laying the sword down, he began reading the book again, and he is said to have read it through twice.
He then fell into so sound a sleep that those who were outside the chamber were aware of it, and about midnight he called <persName id="#his_freedmen">his freedmen</persName> Cleanthes <persName id="#the_physician">the physician</persName> and Butas whom he employed <persName id="#chief">chief</persName> of all in public matters.
He sent <persName id="#butas">Butas</persName> to the sea to examine if all had set sail and to report to him, and he presented his hand to <persName id="#the_physician">the physician</persName> to tie it up, as it was inflamed from the blow which he gave <persName id="#the_slave">the slave</persName>.
And this made them all more cheerful, for they thought that <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> was inclined to live.
In a little time Butas came and reported that all had set sail except <persName id="#crassus">Crassus</persName>, who was detained by some business, and that even he was now all but on board, and that a violent storm and wind prevailed at sea.
Cato hearing this groaned for pity of those who were at sea and he sent Butas again to the sea, to learn if any one were driven back and waited any necessaries, and to let him know.
And now the birds were beginning to sing, and he sank asleep again for a while.
When Butas had returned and reported that all was quiet about the ports, <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName>, bidding him close the door, threw himself on the bed as if he were going to sleep for the rest of the night.
When Butas had gone out, he drew the sword and thrust it beneath his chest, but as he used his hand with less effect owing to the inflammation, he did not immediately despatch himself, and having some difficulty in dying he fell from the bed and made a noise by overturning a little abacus of the geometrical kind that stood by, which <persName id="#his_attendants">his attendants</persName> perceiving called out and <persName id="#his_son">his son</persName> and <persName id="#his_friends">his friends</persName> immediately ran in.
Seeing him smeared with blood and the greater part of his bowels protruding, though he was still alive and his eyes were open, they were all dreadfully alarmed, and <persName id="#the_physician">the physician</persName> going up to him attempted to replace his bowels, which remained uninjured, and to sew up the wound.
But when <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> recovered and saw this, he pushed <persName id="#the_physician">the physician</persName> away, and tearing the bowels with his hands and at the same time rending the wound he died.
LXXI.
In a space of time which one would not have thought enough for all in the house to have heard of the event, there were present at the door the three hundred, and soon after <persName id="#the_people">the people</persName> of <personGrp id="#utica">Utica</personGrp> were assembled, with one voice calling <persName id="#cato_benefactor">Cato benefactor</persName> and <persName id="#saviour">saviour</persName> and <persName id="#the_only_free_man">the only free man</persName>, the only unvanquished.
And this they did though it was told that <persName id="#caesar">Caesar</persName> was advancing; but neither fear nor subserviency towards <persName id="#the_conqueror">the conqueror</persName> nor their mutual differences and quarrels dulled them towards doing honour to <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName>.
They decorated the body in splendid style, and made a pompous procession and interred him near the sea, where a statue of him now stands with a sword in his hand, and then they began to think how they should save themselves and their city.
LXXII.
Caesar hearing from those who came to him that <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> was staying in <personGrp id="#utica">Utica</personGrp> and not flying away, and that he was sending off the rest, while himself and <persName id="#his_companions">his companions</persName> and <persName id="#his_son">his son</persName> were fearlessly going about, thought it difficult to ascertain the intentions of <persName id="#the_man">the man</persName>, but as he made most account of him he advanced with his force by quick marches.
When he heard of his death, it is reported that he said this, "<persName id="#cato">Cato</persName>, I grudge thee thy death, for thou hast grudged me thy safety."
For in fact if <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> had submitted to receive his life from <persName id="#caesar">Caesar</persName>, he would not have been considered to have lowered his own fame so much as to have added to the splendour of <persName id="#caesar">Caesar</persName>'s.
What would have been done is uncertain, but with respect to <persName id="#caesar">Caesar</persName> the milder measures are more probable.
LXXIII.
When <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> died he was fifty years of age save two.
<persName id="#his_son">His son</persName> received no harm from <persName id="#caesar">Caesar</persName>, but he is said to have been fond of pleasure and not free from blame with regard to <persName id="#women">women</persName>.
In <personGrp id="#cappadocia">Cappadocia</personGrp> he had as <persName id="#his_host">his host</persName> <personGrp id="#marphadates">Marphadates</personGrp>, one of <persName id="#the_royal_family">the royal family</persName>, who possessed <persName id="#a_handsome_wife">a handsome wife</persName>, and as Cato stayed longer with them than was decent, he was satirized in such terms as these: "To-morrow <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> goes away, to-morrow thirty days."
And: "Porcius and <personGrp id="#marphadates">Marphadates</personGrp>, <persName id="#friends">friends</persName> are two, but Psyche one."
For <persName id="#the_wife">the wife</persName> of <personGrp id="#marphadates">Marphadates</personGrp> was named Psyche (Soul).
And again: "Of noble blood and splendid fame, Cato has a royal Soul."
But he blotted out and destroyed all such ill report by his death; for while fighting at <personGrp id="#philippi">Philippi</personGrp> against <persName id="#caesar">Caesar</persName> and <persName id="#antonius">Antonius</persName> in defence of liberty, and the line was giving way, not deigning either to fly or to secrete himself, but challenging <persName id="#the_enemy">the enemy</persName> and showing himself in front of them and cheering on those who kept the ground with him he fell after exhibiting to <persName id="#his_adversaries">his adversaries</persName> prodigies of valour.
And still more, <persName id="#the_daughter">the daughter</persName> of <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName> being inferior neither in virtue nor courage (for she was <persName id="#the_wife">the wife</persName> of <persName id="#brutus">Brutus</persName> who killed <persName id="#caesar">Caesar</persName>) was both privy to the conspiracy and parted with life in a manner worthy of her noble birth and merit, as is told in the Life of Brutus.
<persName id="#statyllius">Statyllius</persName>, who said that he would follow <persName id="#cato">Cato</persName>'s example, was prevented indeed at the time by <persName id="#the_philosophers">the philosophers</persName>, though he wished to kill himself, but afterwards he showed himself most faithful to <persName id="#brutus">Brutus</persName> and most serviceable at <personGrp id="#philippi">Philippi</personGrp>, and there he died.
